<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word to Londons provinciall assembly. Or, a view of some passages in the ministers late vindication of their government. To which is added a vindication of the Covenant against all intruders and opposers. / By Nehemia Cent:.</title>
            <author>Cent, Nehemiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E586_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865443</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 90:E586[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word to Londons provinciall assembly. Or, a view of some passages in the ministers late vindication of their government. To which is added a vindication of the Covenant against all intruders and opposers. / By Nehemia Cent:.</title>
                  <author>Cent, Nehemiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 [i.e. 48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Author, and are to be sold at the Crowne in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 24 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Page 48 mesnumbered 40.</note>
                  <note>Nehemiah Cent is a pseudonym.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Word to <hi>LONDONS</hi> Provinciall Aſſembly. OR, A View of ſome Paſſages in the Miniſters late <hi>Vindication</hi> of their <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added A Vindication of the Covenant againſt all Intruders and Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> NEHEMIA CENT:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 62.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> For Sions ſake will I not hold my peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake will I not reſt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 5.30.31.</hi>
                  </bibl> A wonderfull and horrible thing is committed in the Land: The Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts beare rule by their meanes, and my people love to have it ſo, and what will yee doe in the end thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 23.39.40.</hi>
                  </bibl> Therefore behold, I, even I will utterly forget you, and I will forſake you, and the City that I gave you, and your Fathers, and caſt you out of my preſence.</p>
               <p>And I will bring an everlaſting reproach upon you, and a perpetuall ſhame which ſhall not be forgotten.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold at the Crowne in Popes-head Alley, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117684:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117684:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I conſider the diviſions that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, ariſing from the diverſities of the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and opinions of men, and the dangers we are in thereby, it makes me feare, we are fallen into thoſe times, which are ſaid ſhall come, which are called perillous times, 2 <hi>Timothy</hi> 3.1. <hi>Men ſhall be lovers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Covetous, Boaſters, Proud, Blaſphemers, &amp;c.</hi> And from ſelfe it is, that men ſeek to ſet up themſelves, and the brats of their owne braine, and fall ſo in love with them, as for the obtaining of their deſires, they run deſperate hazzards, for they are not willing that truth ſhould prevaile, nor thoſe that ſeeke to hold it forth in their practiſes; and therefore they indeavour to make all ſtoope to them: and to that end they uſe all meanes to obtaine their owne wills, and therefore they that ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they indeavour to loade with reproach, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and to draw off peoples hearts from them, and after them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nay, they give many privy nips at the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, under ſmooth pretences, and expreſſions, which is very ſad to thinke of; eſpecially comming from ſuch men as Miniſters, and Elders, and in the Province of <hi>London,</hi> the cheife City and place in the Kingdom, which makes it the more dangerous, and the more to be lamented. And therefore my deſire is, for thy good, that thou wouldeſt begge of God ſuch a heart that thou maieſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what our Saviour ſayes, that thou wouldeſt <hi>Take heed what thou doeſt heare</hi> or read, and that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Beleeve not every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb facs="tcp:117684:3"/> but try the ſpirits whether they be of God or not,</hi> and that, <hi>try all things, and hold faſt that which is good:</hi> For it is ſaid by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that <hi>there ſhall ariſe many falſe Prophets, and ſhall deceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nay, if it were poſsible, they ſhould deceive the very Elect;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had need watch and pray, that <hi>we enter not into temptation;</hi> and therefore be very carefull when thou art to read the booke called <hi>the vindication of the Presbyterian Government and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> for although there be many faire words, and pretences, yet thou ſhalt finde many things in it, which, if thou doeſt not take heede, may prove very dangerous unto thee, for there thou mayeſt ſee godlineſſe pretended, but thoſe that deſire to walke up to the power of godlineſſe, reproached, and called Schiſmaticks, &amp;c. and charged with rending the Church, and people warned to reject their doctrine; and many ſuch kind of aſperſions they are laden with, in many parts of that booke, which is ſad to thinke of. But my intent is to ſpeake but a word to them in this booke, nor to ſay more of them at this time. But my intent is as thou maieſt ſee, mainly, to anſwer a booke that was ſet out with forty ſeven of their names to it, which I think, were all of the ſame ſociety: the reaſon that cauſes me to thinke ſo, is, becauſe many of them, are known to be of them, and yet there is not a word ſpoken againſt their proceedings in that booke, which may give occaſion to fear they are all of one mind, which is ſad to think of, there being ſo much ſin in it, and that thou mayeſt not think it ſtrange that it ſhould come forth row ſo long after: I had brought it neare to a readineſſe for the Preſſe a good while ſince, but ſeeing ſo many Anſwers come to it, I reſolved to let it alone. But now ſeeing a book come forth with ſuch a dreſſe, as <hi>A Vindication of the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Miniſtery,</hi> I tooke it and did read it, and finding ſtill the ſame frame of ſpirit as before, ſo farre as I was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, although it were in a ſmoother way; It put me upon thoughts to put forth what I had formerly taken ſome paines in, eſpecially concerning the Nationall Covenant, it being that
<pb facs="tcp:117684:3"/> which I perceive is their ſtrong hold to runne unto, upon all occaſions; and alſo that is one of their maine Pillars to beare them up, in what they do ſpeake and write, againſt ſuch as walk more ſtrictly in the wayes of God then themſelves doe: And beſides, I perceive that many of thoſe, that I beleeve, fear God, are much ſtumbled at it, and cauſed to thinke and ſpeake evill of the preſent Parliament and Army for their late actings; and therefore for the vindication of the Covenant, Parliament, and Army, and yeelding ſome little light to the godly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I have brought it forth, that ſo if it bee the will of God, people may bee more ſettled in the way the Lord hath caſt us into, and give him that praiſe which is his due, and their duty to give him.</p>
            <p>And that it may appeare, neither the Parliament nor Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in what they have acted, nor the godly people in what they have Petitioned, have broken the Covenant; eſpecially in ſuch a manner, as ſome would make the world beleeve they have: but thoſe that cry out ſo of the breach of Covenant, are the greateſt breakers of it themſelves; and therefore that prejudice may bee taken off from the Parliament, Army, and godly people, and the thoughts of unbyaſſed Readers may bee eſtabliſhed, and thoſe that have beene, and are the great Cenſurers of others, may come to ſee their ſinne, and bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take the ſhame of it; and ſo ceaſe to condemne others, and learne to condemne themſelves, by owning their owne ſinnes, and that the conſideration thereof may be a meanes to ſtop them from ſuch high and violent courſes, and alſo from ſuch uncharitable ways and practiſes. And others may be kept from doing or approving theſe or the like practiſes, is, and ſhall bee my earneſt deſire.</p>
            <p>And therefore, Chriſtian Reader, my deſire is, that thou wouldeſt reade this booke with ſuch a frame of ſpirit as may cauſe thee to read it with judgement and conſideration of every
<pb facs="tcp:117684:4"/> part of it, ſo as to be willing to ſee the truth, and to ſtoope to it, ſo as thou mayeſt underſtand, love, and practiſe it: and therefore my deſire is, thou wouldeſt deſire of God an humble and meeke heart, to read withall, that he may teach thee, for he hath promiſed to teach the humble, and guide the meeke to glorie, and that hee may deale ſo by thee, ſhall be the prayer of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Jeſus.</hi> NEHEMIA CENT:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY reaſon of the Authours abſence, many groſſe miſtakes have eſcaped th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, therefore thou art intreated in the reading of this little booke to have recourſe to this Errata which will rectifie the ſenſe:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 2: <hi>line</hi> 16: <hi>read</hi> unto. <hi>l:</hi> 38: <hi>r:</hi> commend. <hi>p:</hi> 4: <hi>l.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1 <hi>r:</hi> abhor. <hi>l:</hi> 15: <hi>after</hi> courſe <hi>adde</hi> in you. <hi>p:</hi> 5: <hi>l:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>after</hi> you <hi>adde</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſider. <hi>p:</hi> 10: <hi>l:</hi> 25: <hi>af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er blood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dde</hi> blood. <hi>p:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>l:</hi> 18 <hi>at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d r:</hi> that is. <hi>p:</hi> 16: <hi>l:</hi> 12: <hi>r:</hi> might: <hi>p:</hi> 18: <hi>l.</hi> 38: <hi>l:</hi> break not the Covenant. <hi>p:</hi> 19: <hi>l.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>r:</hi> hearers. <hi>p:</hi> 20: <hi>l:</hi> 5: <hi>dele.</hi> formerly, <hi>p:</hi> 22: <hi>l:</hi> 19. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the</hi> 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. dealt with in juſtice. <hi>p:</hi> 31: <hi>l:</hi> 27: <hi>r:</hi> they begin in their way. <hi>p:</hi> 27: <hi>l:</hi> 35. <hi>at the beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p:</hi> 31: <hi>l:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> in. <hi>l:</hi> 36: <hi>r:</hi> Jehue's. <hi>p:</hi> 34: <hi>l:</hi> 21 <hi>after</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>adde</hi> they. <hi>p:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7: <hi>l: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>: after</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, <hi>and r:</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 39: <hi>l:</hi> 5: <hi>r:</hi> that God, <hi>p:</hi> 40: <hi>l:</hi> 1: <hi>r:</hi> reall evill <hi>inſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of</hi> as wel. <hi>l:</hi> 33: <hi>r:</hi> tremble. <hi>p:</hi> 42: <hi>l:</hi> 38: <hi>r:</hi> that.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117684:4"/>
            <head>A VVORD to <hi>LONDONS Provinciall Aſſembly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have lately ſeene a Booke called, <hi>A Vindication of the Presbyterian Government and Miniſtery;</hi> with many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to Miniſters, and Elders, and people, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with you, or ſeparating from you, which I took and read over, and that without contempt, mocking, or ſcoffing; which when I had conſidered, I ſaw no cauſe I ſhould, for I ſaw more cauſe of mourning, then of ſcoffing, and of pitying of you, then of contempt, and of praying the Lord to bring your hearts into a better frame then of mocking: And therefore I could but wonder whence ſuch ſuſpicions ſhould ariſe in you; and when I had a little conſidered, I could not tell, except it were from your own experience in your practices; for when I conſidered the ſubſtance of the Booke, I ſaw that which did make me thinke you had not read the Booke of that Reverend Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> about Church-government, or if you have, you have ſlighted it at the beſt; for had you read it with a ſound and ſerious ſpirit, weighing well what he hath ſaid, it will fully anſwer many of your allegations, and take away many of your founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you ſeeme to build upon in your Book: And for ſcoffing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, I ſhould have wondred whence you ſhould have ſuch thoughts, but that I conſider your frame of ſpirit in your former Booke, from which it muſt ariſe, or elſe from the guilt of your owne conſciences of what you then did, which you may feare will render you juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible: at leaſt you might feare it could not be eſteemed, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much of that ſpirit that did ſhew it ſelfe in the former Booke: for although there be many good things in it, and many glorious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, yet there is ſo much <hi>Collaquintida</hi> in it mixed, as may make it very dangerous to the takers, if they take not good heed: And the truth is, it came out unſeaſonably; for if you intended to ſet out a Vindication, you ſhould have ſtayed untill you had firſt ſet out a book
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117684:5"/> of your acknowledgement and humiliation for what you had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo ſinned in, that ſo you might have given ſatisfaction to thoſe that you had offended, and then vindication might have come in ſeaſon, for you muſt think it is not forgotten, and if you had done ſo, it would have been paſt over, and forgotten of thoſe that are the people of God; whereas now they ſee there is cauſe ſtill of applying of more of what you had formerly, that if it be poſſible you may at the laſt come to ſee your ſinne, and mourne, and give ſatisfaction for it, which is one end of the writing of this booke, or at leaſt in committing it to the Preſſe; and another end is, to undeceive the people in that ſtrong hold which you thinke you have againſt them, at leaſt you have made many beleeve ſo, which is the breach of Covenant: for it may hold forth a little light to cauſe them to ſee the Covenant is not broken ſo as you would make them beleeve, eſpecially not by thoſe perſons that you ſo cry out againſt for breaking of it; but that the breach will returne upon your ſelves, although in all your writings ſtill you flye upon that, it being one main thing you center upon in this booke of yours, and by which, and in which, you take occaſion to ſet up your ſelves, and to fling filth upon others; And indeed, you had more need to have condemned your ſelves, then to ſet up your ſelves; and it would have beene more for the glory of God, and the peace and comfort of your owne ſoules, and more to the furtherance of the worke you are going about, which you would have all to conforme unto you in; for all wiſe humble men will thinke the worſe of your way, or at leaſt ſuſpect the more, becauſe you ſeeke ſo much to ſet up your ſelves, for they may feare, and that juſtly, the Lord will not honour you ſo much as to ſhew you the patterne of his houſe; for they can ſee what the Lord ſayes, Ezek. 43.10, 11. <hi>If they be aſhamed of all that they have done, then ſhew them the patterne of the houſe, the in-goings, and the out-goings, and the whole faſhion thereof, and all the Ordinances thereof, and the figures, and all the Lawes thereof, &amp;c.</hi> So if you had publiſhed your ſhame, for what you had ſo ſinfully done before, then you and we might have had hope the Lord would have ſhewed you the patterne of his houſe; for as you ſay of your Presbyterian way, may be truly found of a Church way, it is hard to finde, and more hard to follow, for it is very difficult, and the Lord muſt ſhew it us, or elſe we can never finde the right way; for I feare your way is too eaſie and broad to be the right way: and hee hath made no promiſe to ſhew them the way, that ſeeke to command, and ſet up themſelves. I hope you have not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that exhortation, <hi>Let another praiſe thee, and not thy owne ſelfe;</hi> and you know what our Saviour faith of him that ſets up himſelf above others;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117684:5"/> and who it was that ſaid, <hi>Come ſee my zeale, and is thy heart right as mine is,</hi> it had beene well for him if his heart had beene ſo right as his was which he ſpake to; the Lord give you hearts to examine if there be not too much of that ſpirit in you, it doth ſo much ſhew it ſelfe in the other booke, and this alſo: And may not the former inſtances ſuit you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you, and thoſe, at leaſt ſome of them, whom you ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, and count ſo dangerous perſons, whom you load with ſo many ſad aſperſions, as rending the Church, and hindring of Reformation, and of Schiſme; and warn your people to take heed of them, and of their doctrine, as being ſtrict above what is written, &amp;c. And does not all this ſhew what is formerly ſaid is apparent; the Lord help you to conſider it, that ſo you may take heed how you load others with ſuch aſperſions, eſpecially ſuch as your owne conſcience will tell you, walke with God in uprightneſſe. Would it not be better for you to lay before them the truth of your waies by the word of God, and confute them by the word of God if you be able ſo to doe. But your taking this courſe, will give wiſe men to thinke or at leaſt to feare you are not able ſo to doe, or elſe that you have not found by experience the power of the truth of God in your ſelves; for if you had, you ſhould not need to feare, but that it is of farre more power to convince, and prevaile with perſons, then all ſuch waies as you take: for all arguments, although they be according to the word of God, are not able to convince any, except the Lord go with it by his Almighty power; and therfore not ſuch kind of courſes as theſe be, which his word allows not of; and therefore you cannot have the leaſt hope to prevaile with perſons by them, but you may fear the Lord will appeare againſt you for them, and ſo blaſt you and your wayes, which you ſeek to ſet up by ſuch kind of doings. I dare not think you are ſo little acquainted with the Lord and his power, that he puts forth in his word, when it is purely and truly held forth, as that he is not able and willing to vindicate his owne truth, when it is held forth in an humble manner, without ſuch ſinfull waies as you take; nay aſſuredly, he will never owne, much leſſe goe out with ſuch waies.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore, feare and tremble to goe on in them; for it is juſt from him that you ſhould not onely loſe your labour, but ſhould meet with diſgrace, and if not contempt for your ſo doing, for God will reſiſt you in ſuch waies.</p>
            <p>And beſide, the perſons you write to exhort, I hope have not lived ſo long within the bounds of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> where the word of God hath been ſo long taught, and in ſuch a manner, as it hath beene, and is ſtill taught by ſome faithfull Miniſters of the word of God, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117684:6"/> they have learned to eſteeme more of one Argument out of the Word of God, then of thouſands of ſuch kind of expreſſions; nay I hope they have learned to know the Lord above ſuch kind of expreſſions in ſuch a way, and therefore all ſuch who are godly will be ſo farre like unto him as they will doe the like, eſpecially when they are brought forth againſt the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the juſt, as your owne Conſciences cannot but tell you theſe be, as hath been formerly ſaid, at leaſt ſome of them, and therefore you muſt not thinke to prevaile with any that feare God by ſuch Arguments, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſuch revilings, and I deſire, for your ſakes, you be not judged at the laſt day for Raylers; and I feare, you ſee ſo much your ſelves, that if thoſe you ſo ſpeake againſt, if they ſhould ſpeake ſo of you, it would be eſteemed rayling by you, and that you would make the world take notice you did ſo eſteeme them; but bleſſed be the Lord they doe not ſo, nor I hope wil not deale ſo by you, but will rather ſay, the Lord rebuke you or rather him that furthers ſuch courſes; and alſo pray that the Lord would pleaſe to honour you ſo farre as to make you ſee the evill of ſuch waies, and be humble, and alſo will bring the Word of God, and ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments therefrom, as the Lord may be pleaſed to goe with all as may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, and all thoſe to whom you write, and all thoſe that ſhall read what you write, as you and they may have cauſe to bleſſe God, for while they live in this world, and to all eternity, and be a meanes to make you and them to ſtudy, and pray the Lord to bring your hearts into ſuch a frame, that you may be willing to finde, and alſo to ſubmit unto the way that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath appointed his people to worſhip him in; which I hope will be the end and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yme of all ſuch as take pen in hand to write, to anſwer you in this Book, that ſo truth, and not victory, and the glory of God, and his Will may be ſubmitted unto, and not their owne wills may be obtained of all that love the Lord Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in ſincerity, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and love procured therein, and contention and diviſions may ceaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and that we may come to ſerve him and one another in love, that ſo the Lord Jeſus may take deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht in us, and dwell with us, and in us, and among us, while as he ſhall ſee we ſeeke not our owne ends but his glory, walking in ſelfe deniall and humility, and keeping to his truth exactly; and not doe as you have done, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rne people to reject ſuch doctrines as hold forth a ſtrictneſſe above what is written, and therein bring in all ſuch as teach, that whoſoever will enter into Church Fellowſhip muſt firſt take a Church Covenant.</p>
            <p>I pray conſider if it be not neceſſary they ſhould ſo doe, for are not all men free where they will ſit down and dwell, and when they are ſet down, are they not ſtill free whether they will joyne to the Church or not?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117684:6"/> and if they doe not, if they offend you may tell them; if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to heare you, goe and tell the Church, and if they ſend for him, if he refuſe to come, you can proceed no further againſt him by your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and what is meant by joyning, if it be not by covenanting to walke together with the Church in the waies of the Goſpel? and if a perſon ſo doe, then you have power over him; ſo as the Covenant gives you all the power you have over a perſon to exerciſe the Church Diſcipline upon him, or elſe you have none; and if you have not power over them that are in the Church, then wherefore is Church Diſcipline? and therefore the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant giving you that power, it muſt needs be neceſſary; for that the Church hath ſuch a power is written, and muſt exerciſe it upon the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Brother, and therefore by neceſſary conſequence from Scripture-grounds, there muſt be a Church Covenant, which you may ſee far more at large, and more clearly inreverend M. <hi>Hookers</hi> Book of the ſurvey of Church Government, and therefore it is not a doctrine above what it written, and therefore not to be rejected; but ſuch as we muſt have an eare to heare, and a heart to beleeve, being agreeable to the Word of God; and for what you ſpeake of the Lords Supper, that there is more required then freedome from ignorance and ſcandall, if you meane groſſe ignorance and ſcandall it is a truth, and ſuch a truth as is written, and the Lord hath a mouth to ſpeake, and therefore we muſt have an eare to heare, and a heart to beleeve, and therefore it ought not to be rejected; for are we not bidden to examine our ſelves, and is it not neceſſary to diſcerne the Lords Body, and alſo to know the danger if we doe not come worthily? all which, perſons groſly ignorant, or groſly ſcandalous, cannot, nor will not doe; and if you meane by freedome from theſe that we ſhould be wholly free, then except you be able to prove what you ſay againſt any that they teach ſo, it is a ſlander, and that which you have cauſe to acknowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of, eſpecially you having put it in print that it may come abroad in the world, for we know none require any qualifications above theſe; and therefore I pray conſider, if beſide the ſlander of that you hold forth be not dangerous to your ſelves, and thoſe you have written to, and alſo to as many as ſhall read your Book, and which is worſe, derogatory to the glory of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d And then conſider, how you will anſwer for it before him at that great and dreadfull day, when you ſhall be called forth, and muſt appeare to anſwer for all you have done in the body. And whereas you ſpeake of perſons caſting reproaches upon the Miniſters of Chriſt, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by this little that hath been ſaid, if you may not feare it may be a juſt hand of God againſt you that people ſhould ſo doe; as alſo if you doe but look whether you have not gone before them by your owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117684:7"/> to lead them ſo to doe, for have you not done ſo? witneſſe what hath been already ſaid of your dealing with others, and then is it a wonder you ſhould meet with it your ſelves? nay, have you not reproached them with unſeemly names, as calling them Sectaries, and Schiſmaticks; nay, have you not gone againſt the light of your owne Conſciences in what you have done, while as they walke peaceably and conſcientiouſly among you in the waies of God, and ſo you have done worſe then thoſe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, which have ſpoken ſo of you; for although it be not to be approved of, that any ſhould reproach you, but condemned, yet conſider if you have not given them juſt cauſe ſo to doe, which I hope by that time you have read this Book, and conſidered, you will ſmite upon your owne hearts and confeſſe you have, and then I hope you will take the counſell is given you elſewhere in this Book, and learne better language hereafter, eſpecially to publiſh it to the world; for I cannot but beleeve you are convinced not only they are the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rvants of Chriſt, but the Miniſters of Chriſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſome of them: and what a ſad thing it is that Miniſters ſhould ſo ſpeake of Miniſters, if this be not rending of the Church, and if it may not be called Schiſme, yet if it be not very like it, let the judicious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, and impartiall Reader judge; as alſo what hurt this may do in every place where it ſhall come, eſpecially it being in print; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you conſider what root this came from, if it be not from pride, as hath been formerly ſaid? for why ſhould you thus cry out, and ſpeake ſo much evill of them, becauſe they will not ſtoop and come in to you, and be of your judgement, and goe on in your way; why may they not as well finde fault with you, becauſe you doe not condiſcend to them, eſpecially if you conſider what hath been ſaid, and what is in reverend Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> Book, and we may the rather beleeve they are in the right way then you, becauſe they hold forth moſt ſelfe deniall, and I beſeech you therefore again and againe, take heed you be not found raylers at the Churches and people of the living God, and ſuch as he will owne at the laſt day, and bring them in Judgement againſt you; for you know what became of him that railed on the Hoaſt of the living God, there was a ſtone came and made him fall upon the earth and he was deſtroyed: But yours being not only of the Hoaſt, but alſo of the Miniſters of the Lord Chriſt; that ſtone that is ſpoken of, which is hewn out of the Mountaine will fall upon you and cruſh you, if you be found ſuch; for the Church is compared to an Army with Bannors, and the Lord Chriſt is their Generall, before whom you will never be able to ſtand if he come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: which the Lord in his abundant mercy give you hearts to conſider of, together with all the arguments beſides, that are written in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117684:7"/> this book, and alſo al that hath bin, or ſhall be written in any other book that ſome, or all of them may be ſo gon along withall by his bleſſing &amp; the powerfull working of his Spirit, as that it may throughly convince you of your ſin, that he may follow it on to bring you to true humiliation, and acknowledgement of it in ſuch a publike way as may be to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory, and your owne peace and true comfort, that ſo it may be pardoned, and your ſoules everlaſtingly ſaved; and that it may doe good, and keep from evill all thoſe to whom it ſhall come, whom he ſhall give a heart to read it impartially, which is the whole aime and deſire of him who cauſed it to be printed, and to that end ſhall follow it with his prayers ſo farre as the Lord doth aſſiſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have written much more in anſwer to your Vindication, but that I having written ſo much in anſwer to your former Booke, and not doubting but that others farre more able and fit will give you full anſwers, unto whom I ſhall willingly leave it, and pray they may doe it effectually, and with ſuch ends and aimes as the Lord who is the ſearcher of all hearts may be pleaſed to goe along with them and it, as it may become effectuall to his glory, the peace and comfort of their ſoules, and the good of all the Church and people of God; and ſo for this time I ſhall commit it to him, and wait and expect his gracious anſwer by his bleſſing upon it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Covenant vindicated againſt all Intruders and Oppoſers.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gentlemen;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu have in a Letter of yours (to the Generall and his Councell of war) laid many things to the charge of the Army, and ſo as you make them great offenders, which you and all others have cauſe to conſider of, becauſe the things therein contained do concerne the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and many of the godly party in the Kingdome; they having been ſuch as have been approved of by the one, and petitioned by the other, and therefore it will be good to conſider them, againe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, before we cenſure them, for God does uſually reveal his mind to them that feare him: and therefore if it be the mind of God they have done, then <hi>I</hi> hope you will ſee, that you have gone againſt the mind of God in what ye have done (in this your accuſation of them) and that you have cauſe to be humble, and give what ſatisfaction you can; although I feare you cannot hardly be able to give ſatisfaction to the full.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117684:8"/>
               <p>And therefore it will not be amiſſe to conſider what our condition was before the beginning of theſe troubles, and what it hath been ſince. You may remember before theſe troubles began, there were many ſore burthen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which lay upon the hearts of the honeſt party in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which, I ſuppoſe, many of you, if not all, were ſenſible of: I am ſure if you were not, ſome were ſo ſenſible of them that they choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forſake their dear native Country, and hazzard themſelves in a wilderneſſe among wild-men and wild-beaſts, and many other ſadde hazzards to themſelves and families, to be at freedome from them, and injoy their liberties, to honour God in his own wayes, rather then to indure thoſe burdens: for they ſaw, and you might ſee alſo, that the whole law of God was violated in ahigh degree; which ſtands in our duty toward God in knowing, and worſhiping of him, in a right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, according to his Word, and in our duty we owe to men, with whom we have to deal, which in ſum, is that our Saviour tels us, is the fulfilling of the whole law, and in theſe are the priviledges of all thoſe that fear God, that they may injoy both theſe as God doth require, and you being hindred in both theſe, your burdens were inſufferable, but we had no remedy, but your only hope, under God, lay in a Parliament to helpe to right us, and releive us in this condition, and therefore our deſires were earneſt for a Parliament, which through many difficulties the Lord was pleaſed to grant us, and then you thought you had a power to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile that power which before did oppreſſe you, which made you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by this means you might be ſet at liberty from your fore named burthens, and procure a freedome in both, to act for the glory of God; but when it came to the pinch, you know what was done by that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which did hold you in bondage, what plotting and contriving there was, againſt that power which ſhould act for your liberty, as hath appeared by many Declarations of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>liament, that they were ſuch as tended to bring in Popery and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>And it doth appeare further by their late Declaration of the 18 of <hi>January</hi> laſt, where it appeares they ſought unto the King, by making their complaints to him by humble Petitions, and Remonſtrances, and Declarations, but all in vaine; and the obſtruction did continually flow from the Kings immediate deſigne, which did appeare in what he did offer to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, and alſo to the <hi>Scots,</hi> as to give them the four Northern Counties, and the plunder of the City of <hi>London,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, in the ſixth page of the fore named Declaration.</p>
               <p>And further it appeares in that he did in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as there it appears. And further his withdrawing from the Parliament, and ſetting up his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117684:8"/> Standard againſt it, and then they being in ſuch a condition they were fain to raiſe an Army, and then ſeeing in what manner they were oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and fearing the people might be drawn aſide, they did enter into a Covenant themſelves, and cauſed the people ſo to do, that by this they might have a ſtrong tye upon them, to bind them to do that they were in duty bound to do, which was to hold for the glory of God, to maintain that in the Priviledges of the Parliam. whereby the Law of God might be preſerved: which cauſed the moſt part of the godly people in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be willing to enter into that Covenant: and I hope it was that you aimed at in perſwading and ſtirring up the people ſo to do; and therefore the Covenant was taken to that end, and muſt be ſo taken, if lawfully taken, according to the rule which we muſt ſweare, in Truth, in Righteouſneſſe, and Judgement: and therefore there muſt not be a Covenant, that any part thereof ſhould croſſe that end: ſo as the King and his party muſt be preſerved to that end and no further, and the Priviledges of Parliament and the liberties of the Kingdome, muſt be preſerved for that end and no further, for all muſt ſtoop to that maine end, the glory of God, becauſe therein conſiſts all our Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and peace, and what ever elſe is good: So, as if the King, or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in part, or in whole, or any other perſon, or perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, will go contrary to that end, the Covenant binds to take them to be enemies to God, and the peace and Priviledges of Parliament, and Kingdome.</p>
               <p>For it may be ſaid, as ſometime <hi>Jehu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Jehoram, what peace can there be, &amp;c.</hi> So we may ſay, what peace can there be ſo long as Idolatry or oppreſſion remaines, or is ſought to remaine in the Kingdome. And the Covenant does bind all that have taken it to do their utmoſt <hi>(to bring all ſuch to tryall, that they may receive condigne puniſhment)</hi> and that with their lives and eſtates, and not only ſo, but they muſt aide and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt all thoſe that doe take and bring any ſuch to tryal, to receive ſuch condigne puniſhment, as ſhall be according to their deſerts: And therefore if the King will go contrary to that forenamed end, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, wherein ſtands the Priviledges of Parliament, and the peace and liberties of the Kingdome, he muſt be brought forth; or if any in Parliament will do ſo, they muſt be brought forth, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever: for there is none excepted in the Covenant. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you preached, curſe you <hi>Meroze</hi> becauſe he came not out to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty, and therefore your aime was againſt them principally; aske conſcience if it were not them, for who could have carried on that deſigne but thoſe, and you did well ſo to do, and to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117684:9"/> minde the people of their Covenant.</p>
               <p>And however then your breadth of charity was ſuch, as you might think the King was led by evill Counſell at thoſe times, and therefore you might thinke to preſerve his perſon, if it could and might appeare it was ſo really, but however you were reſolved to go on in acting for the glory of God, &amp; therein for the peace and liberties of the Kingdoms to free them from their former burthens, and therefore he being among them, if he would continue among them, they muſt go out as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as againſt any other, and he might fal by a bullet or a ſword, as well as any other, nay there was more cauſe to go againſt him then againſt any one man; becauſe he was the only man able to carry on ſuch a deſigne by his Authority.</p>
               <p>And for the Parliament, becauſe you ſaw nothing, but that they did act for thoſe ends, you did incourage people, to go fight for them, and their party, againſt the King, and his party, which did oppoſe thoſe ends. But afterward you might ſee apparently, that it was not from his evill Councell alone, but it was from himſelfe: which did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, by his refuſal to hearken to thoſe many Petitions, Declarations, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances, and other proffers made unto him from time to time. Nay when his evill Councell was taken away, he came not to his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but did flye to the <hi>Scots.</hi> Nay, when he was in Priſon, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, notwithſtanding they did condeſcend to a Treaty upon tearmes of diſadvantage, yet he held ſtill to his principles: which had they yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto, they had not onely loſt the Cauſe, for which ſo much blood and treaſure, yea innocent blood of Saints was ſhed, and that in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: but in all liklyhood, they had brought themſelves and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms into a greater and worſer bondage then before: And beſides, they had broken their Covenant in ſo doing.</p>
               <p>And afterwards, when it did appeare that many in Parliament did act ſo as was againſt your fore-named ends, and did ſide in yeelding to the King and his party, then the Army was bound if it were in their power, and ſo all that had taken the Coven went are likewiſe bound ſo far as their power did reach to apprehend them, and bring them to their try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that they might receive condigne puniſhment, and that by their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. So as if it appeare, that the Parliament ſtill ſitting, the Army, and godly party of the Kingdom did deſire and act no other ways then f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the glory of God, in the Priviledges of Parliament, and liberties of the Kingdome, and in diſcharge of their Covenant; then they are ſo farre from deſerving blame for what they have done, as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve incouragement and commendations for what they have done.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117684:9"/> And that they have ſo done, may be ſeen and judged the better, we will ſet down the Covenant at large: which is as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">I. THat you ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, through the grace of God, in your ſeverall places and callings, endeavour the preſervation of the Reformed Religion of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, againſt our common enemies, the Reformation of Religion in the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches, and ſhall indeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to the neareſt conjunction and uniformity in Religion, and Confeſſion of Faith, Forme of Church Government, Directory for Worſhip and Catechiſing, that we and the poſterity after us, may, as brethren, live in faith and love, and the Lord may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in the middeſt of us.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That we ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of perſons, endeavor the extirpation of Popery, and Prelacy, that is, Church Government by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors, and Commiſſaries, Deanes, Deanes and Chapters, Arch Deacons and al other inferiour Officers depending on that Hierarchy, Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine; and the power of god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſſe leaſt we be partakers of other mens ſins, and in danger to receive of their plagues, and that the Lord may be one and his name one, in the three Kingdomes.</p>
               <p n="3">III. We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reality, and conſtancy in our ſeverall vocations, indeavour with our eſtates and lives, mutually to preſerve the Priviledges of Parliament, and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdome: And to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties perſon and Authority in the preſervation of the true Religion, and the liberties of the Kingdome, that the World may bear witneſſe with our conſciences of our true Loyalty; and that wee have no thoughts nor intentions to diminiſh His
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117684:10"/> Majeſties juſt power and Greatneſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. We ſhal with al faithfulneſſe endeavor the diſcovery of all ſuch as have bin, or ſhal be Incendiaries, Malignants or evil Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by hindering the Reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his People, or one of the Kingdomes from another; or making any parties, for faction among the People, contrary to this League and Covenant, that they may bee brought to publicke tryall, and receive condigne puniſhment as the degree of their offences ſhall require, or deſerve, or the Supreame Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories of both Kingdoms reſpectively, or others having pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for that effect, ſhall judge convenient.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And whereas the happines of a bleſſed peace between theſe Kingdoms, denied in former times to our Progenitours, is by the good Providence of God granted to us, and hath been lately conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſettled by both Parliaments, we ſhall each one of us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our place and intereſt, endeavour that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conjoyned in a firme peace and union to all poſterity: and that juſtice may be done upon the wilfull oppoſers thereof, in manner expreſſed in the former Article.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. We ſhall according to our places and callings in this common cauſe of Religion, Liberty, and peace of the Kingdomes, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in the maintaining and purſuance thereof, and ſhal not ſuffer our ſelves directly or indirectly, by what ever combination, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, or terror, to be divided from this bleſſed union and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, whether to make defection to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency, or neutrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, and the good of theſe Kingdomes, and honor of the King; but ſhall all the daies of our lives, zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein againſt all oppoſition, and promote the ſame, according to our power, againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever; and what we are not able of our ſelves to ſuppreſſe or overcome, we ſhall reveale and make knowne, that it may be timely removed or prevented:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117684:10"/> All which we do as in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>Thus you have the Covenant at large, that nothing may be hid, but it may appeare to the Readers view; now let us come to conſider what may be the true meaning of it, as might be in the minds of all that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the nature of a Covenant that tooke it; for every ſuch perſon, I ſuppoſe, will obſerve the rule ſet downe by the Lord, which is, <hi>Thou ſhall ſweare in truth, righteouſneſſe, and judgement;</hi> and according to that, let us looke ſeriouſly at the meaning of it; and ſo much the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many that, I ſuppoſe, doe really ſeeke the good of the Kingdome, are much ſtumbled about it, fearing it is broken by thoſe that have beene the moſt eminent Actors for the Kingdomes good; and partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe who ſhould bee Incouragers of them that have ſo acted, whoſe word goes far, cry out againſt for the breach of Covenant, and make it one of their ſtrong holds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the firſt branch, firſt there is a promiſe and ingagement to maintaine the Scots in that Reformation in Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, Gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnment, which is exerciſed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed among them againſt all common Enemies; ſo as if the common Enemy ſhould diſturb them at any time, the Covenant bindes to go and helpe them (if they ſtand in need) as well as if we were of that Nation; but it doth not at all binde us to their manner of Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government; neither could our Oath have beene lawfull if wee ſhould ſo have ſworne, becauſe we did not know their Worſhip, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and Government, and ſo we could not have ſworne according to the forenamed Rule: but if we ſhould have been ſo weake or ſinfull to have offered to have taken ſuch an oath, you that profeſſe to be our guides, would not have ſuffered us ſo to doe; and much leſſe have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and exhorted us ſo to doe as you did: but to make it ſure, that your meaning might not be miſtaken, you adde, that the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation you would endeavour in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould be accord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches which doe clearly hold forth that your ſelves did doubt whether the Reformation of Religion that is in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, be according to the word of God, or not, or whether it be according to the example of the beſt Reformed Churches; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you would weigh it, and examine it; and in that you did well, and it was a good ſure way for the people, for by that meanes, they might have liberty to try it before they did receive it; and in ſo doing, they might lawfully take ſuch a Covenant: for they might have the word of God to looke into, and by that means they might try the Worſhip,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117684:11"/> Diſcipline, and Government, whether it were agreeable thereunto or not, and alſo might ſee thereby which were the beſt Reformed Churches, for that is an unerring Rule. And you adde, you will likewiſe endeavour to bring the three Kingdomes into the neareſt conjunction and unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Religion: I ſuppoſe your meaning is therein, that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be endeavoured to be as one, according to the Rule formerly ſpoken of (which was ſure) and when you had attained that Reformation in the manner before ſpoken of, you would carry it on with ſo much beauty, in love, humility, and meekneſſe; and alſo by earneſt prayer to God, together with brotherly exhortation, that you would win the Scots to come in, and joyne with you in your way of Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government; and this is the ſubſtance of the firſt Article.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the attaining to this end, you Covenant, that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, you will endeavour to extirpate all perſons and things, that ſhould hinder you in that forenamed Reformation, and way of Worſhip, as Popery, Prelacy, and their adherents, and alſo whatever elſe that is contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe; and alſo that which will not conduce to your forenamed end; and therefore you would doe here, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Away from me ye workers of iniquity, for I will keep the Commandement of my God:</hi> And this was neceſſary for you to doe, to have all the old Rubbiſh removed, that you might the better lay a new foundation: And this I take to bee the ſubſtance of the ſecond branch of the Covenant, and the ſumme of the firſt and great part of it, the glory of God, in the manner of his worſhip.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That you will in like ſincerity, &amp;c. endeavour with your lives and eſtates, the preſervation of the Priviledges of the Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdome, and the Kings Majeſties perſon and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: But all theſe muſt be in the preſervation of the true Religion, and the Liberties of the Kingdome; but I ſuppoſe, you never intended their preſervation no further: ſo as you would preſerve neither Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, nor the perſon, nor Authority of the King, any further, then it might appeare they would preſerve Religion in that way of Reformation, as is in the firſt Article: And alſo the Priviledges of the Kingdome to the ſame end; and indeed therein ſtands the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Parliament, and the true Liberties of the Kingdome; for that is a guide to both, and the preſerver of both; for while wee preſerve the honour of God, we provide for both the other; and there can be no true priviledge, nor liberty, nor ſafety aſſured without that;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117684:11"/> for God is the preſerver of all, and he hath ſaid, <hi>Thoſe that honour me, I will honour, and thoſe that deſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſteemed;</hi> ſo as the juſt power and greatneſſe ſtood in the up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olding of that; and if he went againſt that, his power and greatneſſe was not to be obeyed: for wee ſhould obey God rather then man; and they that were urged to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a command of God by men, have choſen rather to goe into the fire, and into the Den of Lions, rather then to obey Potent Kings, when they were not able otherwiſe to ſhift for themſelves: and the like may be ſaid of any in Parliament that ſhould joyne to doe the like. But your Covenant does directly binde you to ſtand for it in another way, which was by force, if you could, and therefore you ingage your lives and eſtates for the obtaining of it, ſo as if you have not ground out of the word of God ſo to doe, your Covenant was a ſinfull Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and then you had not need to cry out of perſons for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it, but had need to humble your ſelves for the taking of it, and incouraging others ſo to doe: for the Covenant, as it is made, in a true ſenſe, ſeems to me to be kept, and more exactly by them that are cried out againſt, for the breaking of it, then by any of you that ſo cry out, &amp;c. by the Parliament now ſitting, and the Army.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You will with all faithfulneſſe endeavour to diſcover all thoſe that are Incendiaries, and evill Inſtrume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, &amp;c. that ſhall be found to be hinderers of your Reformation of Religion, as beforeſaid, by dividing the King from his people, and the Kingdomes one from another; and that you will bring them to triall that they may receive condigne puniſhment, &amp;c. So as here you binde your ſelves to this, to all whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, if they doe either of theſe, they muſt be brought forth to triall, and therefore if the King, or any party in Parliament, or any other whatſoever, ſhall hinder your Reformation, as aforeſaid, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king factions among the people, or factious, the Covenant bindes to bring them to triall, that they may receive condigne puniſhment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the degree of their offences.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You Covenant, that all that wilfully oppoſe that union made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdomes, upon the termes formerly expreſſed, they muſt be dealt withall according to the manner expreſſed in the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and therefore I appeale to your owne conſciences, if the King did not oppoſe it wilfully, in his not yeelding according to that manner as is formerly expreſſed; and if he did, then how could the Covenant bee kept, if he were not brought forth, according to that maner? and then if the King ſhould, then all thoſe in Parliament that did ſide with him, and endeavour to preſerve him in that way, and give him power ſo to doe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117684:12"/> in part, or in whole, muſt needs be dealt withall after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or elſe the Covenant could not be kept and preſerved.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Covenant bindes not onely to doe all this, in your owne perſons, but to aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that have taken the Covenant in their endeavours to maintaine it as aforeſaid, and this you will doe all the daies of your lives, zealouſly, and conſtantly, againſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; with all your power; and if you cannot doe it your ſelves, you will reveale it, and that timely, to thoſe that may, that ſo you may not be prevented of that great end you aimed at, the glory of God, the true priviledges of Parliament, and the true liberties of the Kingdome; and it muſt needs be thus, or elſe another party that regard none of all theſe, muſt pretend the Covenant that did maintaine the King, and all other in their way, which I hope you would abhor.</p>
               <p>And now let us ſee, whether the Parliament now ſitting, and the Army, have broken this Covenant in this ſenſe or not, or whether they have not kept it; and give me leave to joyn both together, for they are both ingaged a like in what have beene done, becauſe allowed and approved of by both.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And firſt, they have defended the Scots againſt their Enemies, and that notwithſtanding their deſerts to the contrary, and did ſet them in ſuch a poſture, as they might freely act their Reformed Religion in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, and have oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in the breach of Covenant, which they did in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, according as the Covenant did binde them: Alſo the Lord hath made them inſtrumentall ſo to act, as that they have brought <hi>England</hi> into ſuch a poſture, as they may have liberty to act freely in ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches; and are about to ſet <hi>Ireland</hi> in the ſame condition, and would be glad if <hi>Scotland</hi> would doe the like, and they have oppoſed all thoſe that have acted the contrary, ſo far as in them lies, according to this firſt branch of the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They have done as much as in them lies to extirpate Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie; that is to ſay, Government by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. ſo that Hierarchy is to be aboliſhed: and for any thing is yet done, they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to doe the like to all that ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe, which is according to the ſecond branch of the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They have, with their eſtates, and lives, endeavoured to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, in their acting for the glory of God,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117684:12"/> and the priviledges of the Kingdome, and they have ſtood by, and for them that have ſo acted; and for the Parliament to act freely for the glory of God is their greateſt priviledge, and higheſt right; and for the Kingdome to be ſet in ſuch a condition as they may freely worſhip God, and walke in their ſeverall places and callings, in the diſcharge of their duties according to the Word of God, is the greateſt liberty that can befall a Kingdome or Kingdomes, and ſuch a condition have they been inſtrumentall to ſet this Kingdome in at preſent; and that the Kingdome might be eaſed of thoſe burthens hath been their deſire and endeavours by their Remonſtrance and Petitions for many burthens to be removed, and they have endeavoured it by their actings alſo, and ſtill they continue to be ſollicitous that way; and for the Kings Perſon, they did defend it after they had gotten it into their poſſeſſion, and would have defended it ſtill, and his authority alſo, if they could have done it in the preſervation of the true Religion, in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, and the Liberties of the Kingdome; and alſo they would not have diminiſhed his juſt power and greatneſſe, which was to be ſhewed forth in acting for the glory of God in the good of his Kingdomes; but they kept his Perſon from putting forth his authority, power, and greatneſſe in unjuſt waies, and to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdomes in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of them according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches; all which the Covenant doth binde them unto.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They have indeavoured to diſcover Incendiaries, Malignants, evill Inſtruments, that have hindred the reformation of Religion, and ſought to make diviſions; and alſo thoſe that have made Factions, and Parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, and have brought them to triall, that they might receive condigne puniſhment according to the degree of their offences; witneſſe their dealing with Duke <hi>Hambleton,</hi> Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> Lord of <hi>Holland,</hi> Lord <hi>Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the chiefe of thoſe that roſe in <hi>Wales;</hi> nay, they have not ſpared the King himſelfe, ſo faithfull have they been in performance of their Covenant, nor have they ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red any in Parliament that have acted that way.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They have endeavoured that Juſtice might be done upon the wilfull oppoſers of the peace and union made between the Kingdomes; witneſſe their dealing with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and thoſe that adhered in that deſigne.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They have aſſiſted thoſe that have ſtood in the performance and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this Covenant, againſt all that have oppoſed them, witneſſe their dealing with the <hi>Scots</hi> when they oppoſed, and with the King, and with ſome in Parliament, and with thoſe parties before named, when they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117684:13"/> and as this may be ſaid for the Army, ſo the like may be ſaid for the Parliament that now ſit, who have ſtood to owne them, and have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of what hath been done in theſe kinds, by adding their authority to it: And the like may be ſaid of the godly part of people of the Kingdome, who in their plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have ſhowne themſelves deſtrous thoſe things might be done, whereby the Covenant might be performed, as hath appeared by their many Petitions; ſo that thoſe that are cryed out againſt to be Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant breakers, are thoſe that have been the moſt faithfull in keeping their Covenant of any men in the Kingdome, for the Parliament and Army have not effected theſe things, but in hazard of their eſtates and lives; and yet they have gone thorow with it in ſuch a ſort, that the Generations to come may call them bleſſed, and the preſent Generation (eſpecially the godly party of the Kingdome) may ſay of the preſent Parliament and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as they ſpake of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Thou haſt ſaved our lives. And now let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their accuſers, (which doe ſo cry out of the breach of Covenant, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many people by their ſo doing) and ſee whether themſelves have not broken the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They have been zealous for the preſervation of that reformation of Religion here, that is in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the Covenant doth not at all binde unto here in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for there is a manifeſt difference put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and them, as I conceive; for that here, and in <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and no mention is made of the example of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which ſhewes they were doubtfull of that, but they would be ſure of the beſt Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore they put in according to the Word of God, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the beſt reformed Churches; but you have not endeavoured ſuch a Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that before named (which the Covenant doth binde unto) wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe your taking up with that which is in <hi>Scotland,</hi> you have that manner of Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, confuted by that reverend Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and we cannot but take it, that you are convinced, it is confuted; for if you were not, you would confute his Arguments, and ſhew the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, and untill you have ſo done, we ſhall take what he hath ſaid are ſuch truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as you are not able to anſwer according to the Word of God; and therefore ſuch as you are bound by your Covenant to reforme unto, that being alſo the example of the beſt reformed Churches, ſo far as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doth appeare; which while you doe not confute or reforme to it, let the Reader conſider, if you breake the Covenant, and live in the breach of it; you having liberty ſo to doe, and ſo you have not endeavoured to bring the three Kingdomes to the neareſt uniformity in that way; nay have you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117684:13"/> not, and doe you not oppoſe that Government, although you have not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thoſe Arguments; neither have you ſo confirmed that way you walke in by arguments and grounds out of the Word of God, ſo as might eſtabliſh the people, and leave them without doubt, that you walke in that way which Chriſt hath ſet up to be worſhipped in, now in the times of the Goſpel; but the people muſt take it upon truſt, and ſo can never be ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed in it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Although you have extirpated Popery, and Prelacy, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bulke of it in Church Government, yet if you obſerve diligently ſome paſſages, and Arguments in reverend Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> you may ſee you have not wholly done it, but the ſtumps of that Dagon doe ſtill remaine, and is ſtood for and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden by you; neither have you oppoſed Errors, Superſtition, Schiſme, and Prophaneſſe as you ought to doe; for although you ſpeak againſt them in the generall, you do it in ſuch a manner, that cannot in the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt breadth of charity be taken to come from love, there is ſo much bitternes in the man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of your expreſſions: and in your ſo ſpeaking in the general, you cauſe thoſe that are godlie (in your own Judgements, &amp; free from error as your ſelves be) only they diſſcent from you in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; practiſe, and yet you render them as odious to all your errors, as thoſe that hold and practiſe the greateſt, &amp; are the groſſeſt blaſphemers, and ſo you condemne the generation of the Juſt: and you know what is ſaid, <hi>he that juſtifies the Wicked, and condemnes the Righteous, are both alike in Gods eſteeme.</hi> And what a ſad thing it is, that you that call your ſelves, and would have the people think you are, the Servants and Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Chriſt, ſhould be found in the number of thoſe that ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and condemne his Servants and Children. I beſeech you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how you will anſwer it before him at his comming: for by your preaching, the people are not able to know who you meane, except you meane all thoſe that are not juſt of your Judgement and Practiſe: and therefore, if this be not your mind, diſtinguiſh who they be, that you may not lead people in a miſt, or elſe how can they be convinced, for truth is plaine and open, and therefore you neede not bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor afraid to ſpeak it, and therefore, while you forbear ſo to do, we cannot but looke at you as Covenant-Breakers, except it be ſo you cannot do it, for you have Covenanted to doe what you can: and for oppoſing whatſoever is againſt the power of godlines, I wiſh you do not countenance &amp; incourage ſuch, as if you be asked, or at leaſt if you will ſeriouſly aske your own conſciences you will ſay, they have it not appearing in them &amp; yet you admit them into your choiſe ſocietie, and make them partakers of the choiſeſt Ordinances, and incourage them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117684:14"/> therein, and how this can ſtand with your Covenant, I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p n="3">3 You have not preſerved the Rights and Priviledges of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor the Liberties of the Kingdome as you ſhould have done for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, as doth appeare to the world in Print, and of late it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared more clearlie, for whereas it is their Right, and their greateſt Priviledge to act freely for the glorie of God, you have not encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the ſo acting, nor yet have you incouraged them that have been a meanes to ſet them in ſuch a condition, wherein they might ſo act, and the like may be ſaid for the liberties of the Kingdom: for the Parliament have been acting for the liberties of the Kingdome, and you have not incouraged them therein, and the Armie have been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to ſet them in ſuch a condition, as they might ſo act, and you have not incouraged them therein) for is it not the greateſt libertie to the Kingdom, when they can injoy, to have the Ordinances of God in a powerfull manner according to his Word, freelie and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole, and likewiſe to have Juſtice executed impartially, and it doth not appeare that you have been any meanes to further it notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you know what the Word of God holds forth, that <hi>Juſtice exalteth a Nation:</hi> nay, which might make a gracious conſciencious heart to tremble, to think that you who have incouraged to the taking of the Covenant, and gone before others in ſo doing, by taking it your ſelves; that you ſhould ſo faile, as not to incourage them that have done it. Nay, which is farre worſe, have caſt dirt and filth in the faces of the Parliament; and trampled their honour under your feet, and cauſed all others ſo to doe, ſo far as have laine in your power, and that for their faithfull diſcharge of the Covenant. And you have done the like by the Army, which have ſo often ventured their lives and eſtates, as they have done, and you alſo have Covenanted to doe the like, ſo farre as in you lies, Nay have you not been Incendiaries to ſtirre up people to a diſlike and contempt of Parliament, and Armie, in what they have done? Nay I deſire, that it may not trulie be ſaid (of ſome of you, at the leaſt) that you have in a ſort curſed them: but which is moſt hideous to conſider, have you not prayed to that God (againſt them in their proceedings) to whom you have lifted up your hand, that you would defend and preſerve their honour? whom you know, or ſhould know is juſt, and have plagues in ſtore upon ſuch as crie out againſt others, and doe the ſame things they crie out againſt, eſpeciallie, when as thoſe they ſo crie againſt are innocent of it? and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the preſervation of the perſon and authoritie, I doubt not but you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117684:14"/> have heard of one that ſaith, you have ſet them a King-catching firſt, For was not his perſon in danger of the Bullet, and the Sword in their oppoſing and purſuance of him, whom you had incouraged and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up ſo to doe. And likewiſe for his Authority, did not you incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſtir up perſons to go againſt it, for was not that his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that they went againſt, for if he might have injoyed his Authoritie to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as he would, then he would not have gone from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither would he have gone from place to place, but would have commanded them that came againſt him to lay down Armes, and that was not your intent they ſhould, if he had required them, he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill in the ſame mind he was in when he went away, and could you in that cauſe perſwade and ſtir up perſons to go againſt it, and yet cauſe the ſame perſons to ſweare to preſerve it, without any deſtinction or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation. Nay if he could have come againe to have injoyed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Authoritie, it is very probable he would have cauſed your ſelves to have felt that you had been the oppoſers and not the preſervers of his Authoritie, by your exhorting, and perſwading people to goe againſt him, and in cauſing them to ſwear to ſuch a Covenant, and hee would not have ſuffered you to plaie faſt and looſe with it: but you have limited it, that they ſhould doe it in the defence of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Liberties of the Kingdom, ſo as if he would not do that, then down with his Authoritie, and perſon, and all. And yet when that it is made known, that he continues ſtil in that mind not to yeeld to either, but rather to the utter deſtruction of both (and that after long and patient waiting and bearing with him, and alſo by many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations of him; to ſee if at laſt they might have prevailed) yet I ſay after all this, when he came to be dealt withall according as the Covenant does binde unto, you are ſo farre from incouraging thoſe that have done it, as you cry out againſt them in your preaching and prayers. I beſeech you and the impartiall Reader to judge, whether this be not breach of Covenant in a very high degree.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>I</hi> Beſeech you conſider, if you have not been farre from diſcovering Incendiaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as you are (and I wiſh I might not ſay too tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) cryed out upon for being Incendiaries, and evill Inſtruments, and ſuch as make faction and parties among the people. I beſeech you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whereto many of your paſſages you have in prayer and preaching tend, but to ſuch a thing as to raiſe up in the people a diſlike and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content of the acting of the Parliament and Army, and ſo weaken the hearts and hands of the godlie partie (by occaſioning them to ſin) and ſtrengthening the hearts and hands of the ungodlie, and cauſing them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117684:15"/> to goe on in a higher degree of ſinning, and to ſtir afreſh in their plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and contrivings, and actings againſt God, his truth and people; and is not this breach of Covenant? And for bringing of theſe to triall that they may receive condigne puniſhment; how far have you been from that, when you have oppoſed openly, ſo far as in you lyes, by preaching, praying, and writing; eſpecially this your writing, ſo as the whole world may take notice of your oppoſition: And if thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee not a breach of Covenant, let the Reader and your owne conſciences be judge.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And let it be conſidered, if you have endeavoured in your places that juſtice might be done upon ſuch as did wilfully oppoſe the peace and conjunction of the Kingdome: aske conſcience what you thinke the King aimed at in going to the <hi>Scots,</hi> and refuſing to goe to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, although often deſired and intreated, and in all his other actings of late; were not, and are not the <hi>Scots</hi> conſtant to hold their Church-government, and did not he alwayes oppoſe it, and ſeeke to maintaine Biſhops, if not worſe in <hi>England?</hi> and would not hee then have broken that peace? and if he, then all that party that tooke part with him, muſt be guilty alſo; and your Covenant is, that all ſuch in your places and intereſt, will endeavour they ſhall bee done to in juſtice, as in the former Article; and yet when this is done, you are ſo far from furthering it in your places, as that you cry out againſt thoſe that have done it: And if this be not breach of Covenant, let any impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Reader judge.</p>
               <p n="6">6. You have Covenanted to aſſiſt and defend, according to your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and purſuance thereof; and this you will doe zealouſly, and conſtantly all the daies of your lives: and have you thus done? have you incouraged them that have acted thus? have you preached for them to tell people it was their duty to honour them, they having done ſo much for the good of the land; and that all, eſpecially the godly party, have cauſe to bleſſe God for them? and have you praied for them that the Lord would proſper them, and carry them through couragiouſly? If you have not, conſider if you have not broken Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by not doing what you could for them in your places: but if on the contrary part you have ſpoken evill of them, preached, and praied againſt them, and ſo caſt diſcouragement, and diſhonour upon them, for their ſo acting, then let all that read or heare, judge if this be not noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious breach of Covenant: And the premiſes conſidered, let the Reader iudge, nay let your conſcience judge, if you have not broken every
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117684:15"/> branch of the Covenant: and if you have, then what a condition are thoſe in, that ſhall be a meanes to pull downe heavy wrath upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from heaven by thus preaching and praying againſt themſelves, and condemne themſelves for abominable ſinners, and yet continue in that courſe without repentance? for you muſt needs be the men that are the greateſt Covenant-breakers; which may amaze a gracious heart to thinke of, that you that are ſuch knowing men, and would be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo, eſpecially in matters concerning conſcience, and have beene the promoters, if not the contrivers of the Covenant, and you to be found the greateſt tranſgreſſors, it muſt needs be lamentable, and much weaken the authority of your Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now to come from the Covenant, to the Book it ſelfe:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein they are charged with doing that which was unſeemly, in that they called the Miniſters to a conſultation in matters of Religion, when they ſhould have deſired a conference, and therefore they did not doe that which was ſuitable to them, they being but private perſons.</p>
               <p>To which may be anſwered, they had beene acting according to the Covenant, which they had incouraged them to take, and now they were to act in a higher degree in it; and therefore it was beſeeming them to call them to deſire a conſultation with them who had formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them ſo to doe: But whereas they pretend they were but private perſons, it appeares they were publicke perſons, and ſet in high publicke place; and that by the higheſt Authority in the Land: and therefore it would have beene no diſgrace, or unbeſeeming thing for Miniſters of the Goſpel to have gone to conſult with them, nor would it have neceſſitated them to have beene partakers with them in ſinne, if they could have ſeene any; for they might have witneſſed againſt it, and they might have counſelled the contrary, and ſo might have prevented ſinne, if the way they went in had beene ſinfull; which doth not yet appeare, but the contrary; but they were doing their duty, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Covenant.</p>
               <p>Againe, they ſay they had gone againſt a direct Rule of the word of God: It may be anſwered, they did that which the word of God does require, by your owne confeſſion, for they were performing of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and Oath of God which was upon them; as may appeare in that which hath been formerly ſaid in the matter of the Covenant, in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Parliament in a free condition to act for the glory of God, and the liberty of the Kingdome, in apprehending Delinquents, and bringing them to triall, that they might receive condigne puniſhment according to their deſerts; and ſo to remove them that would hinder
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117684:16"/> them in their ſo acting, all which they are bound unto by their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And whereas it is ſaid, they did that which was out of their ſphere, and ſo made themſelves guilty of ſinne: but they did that which was in their ſphere, for they did that for which they were raiſed and ſent out at the firſt, which was to preſerve the Parliament in ſuch a way as they might act freely for the glorie of God, and therein for the libertie of the Kingdome, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of thoſe perſons and things that might hinder them in their ſo acting, as have formerly been ſaid; and therefore they were not guilty of ſin in their ſo acting.</p>
               <p>And whereas they ſeeme to charge them with former miſcarriages; if you meane their not disbanding when they were bidden: It may be anſwered, it had been ill for the Kingdome (as well as for themſelves) if they had ſo done: and it may be conſidered, if it had not beene un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, they ſhould have ſo done, they not having their wages which was their juſt due; nor an act of indempnity for what they had done (in the extremity of the Wars) againſt ſome Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for which their lives might have been taken away: and beſide, were they not exceedingly provoked, when for deſiring theſe things which were but juſt and equall, they ſhould be accounted enemies to the Kingdome, if they did perſiſt in ſo doing.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid in their late acting, they have reſiſted lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, eſpecially in their Remonſtrance: To which may be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Remonſtrance was in way of propoſalls in ſome things, and the reſt was, that which they might conceive was their duty, grounded upon the word of God, and alſo upon the Covenant, in performance of that; for they might perceive evill inſtruments had beene working, and had brought their deſign neare to a period, againſt the glory of God, priviledges of Parliament, and liberties of the Kingdomes; nay to the ruine of them all, as much as men were able to doe, which they were bound to diſcover, and hinder as much as in them lay, and that by their Covenant, which they faithfully did.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, they oppoſed the Parliament: It may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, they did not oppoſe the Parliament that acted for the end for which they were choſen and ſent, which was for the glory of God, and the Priviledges and liberty of the Kingdome; for they did that which they have approved of ſince, witneſſe their Declaration of the 18 of <hi>January;</hi> for they have ſet them at liberty, ſo to act, by removing thoſe that did hinder them in their ſo acting, which was their duty ſo to doe, and that for which they were raiſed, and ſent out at the firſt,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117684:16"/> and to which the Covenant does binde.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is further ſaid, they ſeized and impriſoned the King, without the conſent or knowledge of the Parliament: To which it may be anſwered, for his impriſonment, it was before they ſeized him, and for their ſeizing of him, it was the Kingdomes ſafety, and their owne alſo, that ſo no greater miſery might come upon the Kingdome, nor upon themſelves: for they might perceive there was an evill affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed party in the Parliament, that might prevaile, and ſo joyne with him; and ſo things might bee brought into a worſe condition then they were before the Wars began; and themſelves, the godly party in the Parliament and Kingdome, might have hazarded to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: which being perceived by them, they were bound to prevent it, and that by their Covenant: And for its being done without conſent of Parliament; if we take the Parliament for thoſe which according to their truſt committed to them, did act for the glory of God, and the liberties of the Kingdome, and if they did not conſent before to it, yet it ſhews they were willing it ſhould be done, becauſe they have never declared openly againſt it, but have approved of it, as it doth appear by their Declaration of the 18 of <hi>January.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, they offered violence to the Members of Parliament, hindring them from ſitting in Parliament, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning ſome of them, though knowne to the Miniſters to be of eminent worth and integrity: It may be anſwered, the violence was onely keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of them backe from ſitting in the Houſe; the reaſon was, they ſaw them to be ſuch as had voted againſt the honour of God, the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, &amp; the liberties of the Kingdom; and that hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, in that they voted to that, which ſince hath been unvoted again, being ſuch as was dangerous to the priviledges of Parliament, and the liberties of the Kingdome, and declared ſo to be by the Parliaments Declaration of the 18 of <hi>January;</hi> and ſo they did not keepe them backe as Members of Parliament, but as acting very dangerouſly againſt the Parliament and Kingdome: And howſoever ſome of them might formerly be knowne to the Miniſters to be of eminent worth and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, yet this act of theirs did appeare otherwiſe to them, that with an impartial eye look upon it; but for ſome of them they had been accuſed, and were faine to forſake the Parliament, and yet they were brought in againe by a ſtrong diſaffected party that were in Parliament, againſt the minde of thoſe that acted for the glory of God, and the true liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kingdom, which afterwards was declared to be of dangerous conſequence, as tending to the deſtruction of Juſtice, and the peace of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117684:17"/> the Kingdome, witneſſe the Parliaments Declaration of the 18 of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary:</hi> and likewiſe many other Votes after they came in, as there it, doth appeare, and therefore there was a cauſe ſome of them ſhould bee impriſoned, and be brought to their triall; and ſo it was that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant binds unto.</p>
               <p>Another thing they lay to their charge, is, the framing a new moddel of Lawes and Government, which is againſt the lawfull Authority that God hath ſet over us &amp; contrary to the obedience we do ow unto them, and thoſe manifold oaths and Covenants, we have bound our ſelves to render to them; and againſt the Law of God alſo: For anſwer to this, is it againſt our Oaths taken, or againſt the lawfull Government, or againſt the authority of Magiſtrates, for men to propound their apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to them when they are ſet in place to make Lawes, ſo as they leave them to themſelves to conſider of, let the impartiall Reader judge; and this is all that is yet done, for there is none of theſe things forced yet: and therefore for any to charge them with it yet, is to judge before the time, and ſo againſt that rule which bids us judge nothing before the time, and againſt the rule of charity that thinketh not evill.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, they have no colour of legall Authority, but meerly upon preſumption of ſtrength to attempt theſe changes: To which it may be anſwered (as to what they have acted by way of Authority) they have a reall authority ſo to act, for they have it from the higheſt Authority in the Land, and it is manifeſtly knowne; and for their ſtrength it was raiſed, as is manifeſted before, which was for the defence of the Parliament, that they might act freely for the glory of God, and the true liberties of the Kingdome: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore they need not act from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but from faith, grounded upon a promiſe, that being their way, and in his alſo, they might looke for protection and preſervation, for he hath promiſed to keep us in all our wayes; and he hath done ſo to this day, and will ſo doe, if they ſeeke his glory as their end, and walke in his way as the meanes.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, they have gone contrary to their truſt, which was to preſerve the Parliament, Religion, and liberties of the Kingdome, and the Lawes: To which it may be anſwered, that which hath beene ſaid before, might be ſufficient: but we may ſay they have done according to their truſt; and if they had not done what they did, they had gone contrary to their truſt indeed, for that was the great truſt for which they were raiſed, to preſerve the Parliament, in acting freely for God, and ſo for Religion, and the liberties of the Kingdome, which elſe might have beene deſtroyed; and as hath appeared by what hath beene ſaid many times before, this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117684:17"/> they have done in their late actings, and therefore they have ſhewed themſelves faithfull and truſty in what they have done, in performing their ingagements.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid, their violence they offered to the Parliament, did exceed that of the Kings by far: For anſwer to this, conſider the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence pretended by them, offered here, was becauſe they kept out ſome perſons that were a hindrance to the Parliament in their acting freely, for the glory of God in the liberties of the Kingdome, and ſuch as had acted againſt the glory of God, and the true liberties of the Kingdome; witneſſe the Parliaments Declaration of the 18 of <hi>January,</hi> by acting in thoſe votes there mentioned, contrary to what had been voted before, and were ſuch as when the Parliament was ſet free to act, they were fain, (for the Kingdomes good and ſafety) to unvote againe: but that of the King, was in demanding thoſe that did appeare to be moſt active for the glory of God, and the good of the Kingdome. And againe, that which the Army did, they were bound to doe by Covenant (as will appeare, if what hath been ſaid be conſidered) but what the King did, was manifeſtly againſt it; &amp; alſo that which they did, was their duty to do, as the cauſe then ſtood, &amp; that which the King did, was that which he ought not to have done; ſo as the violence the King did offer, did as far exceed theirs, as a man that goeth directly contrary to that which the word of God calls for; and a man that goes directly to do, what the word of God does enjoyn; and therefore the Army did what in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they were bound to do; and what the King did, was that which in conſcience h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould not have done.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, they have uſurped Authority over King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: To which it may be anſwered, for that of the King, they were ſet in authority to doe it, and the Covenant did binde them to doe what they did, and ſo no uſurpation; and the like may be ſaid of what they did to thoſe of the Parliament, ſo as they have neither gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the authority that was given them, nor contrary to the end for which it was given them; if that which hath been formerly ſaid, be well weighed, and therefore far from uſurpation.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, they intermeddle with things that belong not unto them; for anſwer, it may be ſaid they did what belonged to them to doe (that which they did being neceſſary to be done) for no other could have done it, becauſe they were not able; and it being in their power to doe it, they were bound to doe it by the Covenant, what they did to the King, and thoſe Members of Parliament, and what they did in their propoſals was lawfull for them to doe in the way they did it, that ſo they might commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117684:18"/> their thoughts to the Parliament thereby; and I never heard that the Parliament did finde fault with them for ſo doing, nor ſo upbraid them as you have done, and yet I thinke it belonged more properly to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to do it, then to you.</p>
               <p>It is further laid to their charge, that they effect that by power which the Laws of God, Nature, and Nations doe not allow; for anſwer, you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Parliament might take up Armes againſt the King and his Party, for their owne defence, which doe warrant them in what they have done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what they did was in ſubordination to the Parliament, as owning them to be above them; for it is plaine, what juſtice was executed upon the King, or hath been upon any other (except that which doth properly belong to them as Souldiers) hath been done by the authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they did but bring them to Triall, which the Covenant did binde them to doe; and they have not hindred the Parliament, much leſſe uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority over them; but they have done that which your ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge they were raiſed to doe, which was to preſerve the Parliament from the King, and ſuch as were evill diſpoſed, and ſo evill inſtruments: nor have the Parliament declared againſt them any ſuch thing, nor ſhewed any diſlike in what they have done, but rather juſtifie what they have done by their Declaration, and this the Covenant calls for, and therefore they are not ſo to be charged.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, they offered violence to the Perſon of the King, contrary to the intention of the Parliament in taking up Armes, and that they diveſted him of his regall Authority; to which it may be anſwered, when the Parliament firſt tooke up Armes, the breadth of their charity, and tenderneſſe of his honour was ſuch, as made them to thinke poſſibly he might be led chiefly on, only by his evill Counſellors; and yet they were more tender over the honour of God, and the priviledges and Liberties of the whole Kingdome; and therefore they raiſed an Army to go againſt him if he would oppoſe that, but if he would forſake thoſe wayes he went in, and come and joyne with them for the honour of God, and the good of the Kingdome, they intended no violence to his Perſon; but if he would not, nor they could not obtaine it no other way, then they reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lved to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence to his Perſon; for their rayſing an Army, and ſending them out, and keeping them in the Field, againſt whom was it but againſt his Perſon and Authority? for who could have been able to have carried on ſuch oppoſition but he? And beſides, he was among them in perſon, and therefore as ſubject to the Bullet and Sword as another man; but afterward when many apparent grounds were, that it was not from his evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours alone, but from himſelfe; as appeared when his Cabinet was taken,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117684:18"/> and after, when his evill Counſell was gone, he went to the <hi>Scots,</hi> and would not come to his Parliament, neither hath he yeelded ſince, as hath been ſaid before, ſo as they who will not bee willfully blinde, may ſee, the Cauſe was otherwiſe, and that which was done, was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and according to the Covenant, to diveſt him of his regall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, for the cheife ground did ſtill remaine as at the firſt; for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the Priviledges, and true Liberties of the Kingdome muſt be maintained which could not have been don otherways, witneſſe the Parliaments Declaration of the 18th. of <hi>January,</hi> and they knew better how the State-affaires ſtood, then you and we doe, beſides con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what is ſaid in Mr: <hi>Cookes</hi> booke, and it will appeare plainly.</p>
               <p>And againe it is ſaid, they being private perſons, ſeeke to overthrow and ſubvert the fundamentall Laws of the Kingdome. For anſwer to the firſt, their being private Perſons, conſider what hath been ſaid formerly, and for overthrowing the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, that is not ſo: for the contrary is declared by the Parliament, for they have ſaid they will maintaine them, what the Armie did, was in propoſalls as hath beene ſaid formerly, and ſo they are not ſubverted and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid, their doings are licencious, tending to the ſubverſion of Religion, Laws, and Liberties of the Kingdome. Anſwer. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of thoſe (eſpecially, that your Letter is directed unto) have not been irregular, if what hath been formerly ſaid be weighed; much leſſe licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo far as they have yet acted, nor have they been to the ſubverſion of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they have acted to the preſervation of all, while they have ſet the Parliament in ſuch a condition, as they may act for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of them all.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, they have gone againſt their Oath and Covenant, in what they have done. For Anſwer, That may ſuffice that is ſaid formerly, they have been ſo far from going againſt them, that the Parliament and Army have kept them better then any in the Kingdome, for they have perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med what the Covenant deſires in a high degree.</p>
               <p>It is againe ſaid, they are fallen into ſuch a condition, as they ſhould not be bidden God ſpeed, nor be wiſhed well in the name of the Lord. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, What ſome dare or will doe I know not, but they have acted and kept the Covenant ſo faithfully of late, as the Parl. and Kingd. eſpecially the godly party in the Kingdom, have cauſe to bleſſe them in the name of the Lord, and to pray for them, for we may not only ſay Inſtrumentally, they have ſaved our lives, but our families, and eſtates that we have, but they have been Inſtrumentall alſo to ſave our liberties, and which is moſt of all, our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117684:19"/> Religion in a more free and full injoyment of it, more then ever before, and this by their late actings; for without this, all the former blood and treaſure had been loſt, and the Cauſe, and all the Kingdom, left in a worſe condition then before.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, they feare they are opening a doore to damnable Errours, Hereſies, and licentious wicked practiſes. For Anſwer, I doe not ſee Cauſe ſo to thinke, much leſſe to ſpeake, but leaſt of all to write ſo, for love thinkes no evill, nor dares not, except it have manifeſt witneſſe, and we are commanded to judge nothing before the time, which Rules I conceive are broken in a very high degree, being divulged to the world, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt perſons as are in ſuch places, and of ſuch deſerts.</p>
               <p>Againe it is ſaid, Religion is made to ſtinke by reaſon of their miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and the faces of Gods ſervants covered with ſhame, and their hearts filled with ſorrow and griefe for it. It may be anſwered, Religion may be made beautifull, and it, and the people of God made a ſweet ſavour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by their meanes, for they have been a meanes to ſet them at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that have power in their hands to give liberty to the people of God ſo to doe: and therefore ſo far from having their faces covered with ſhame, as they may look their enemies in the face with boldneſſe, and ſo far from having their hearts filled with ſorrow, as there is cauſe they ſhould be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with joy and gladneſſe, to thinke, that now thoſe in Parliament may act freely for God, in ſetting his people at liberty to ſerve him according to the Rules of his Word, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches, and that they may act freely alſo in the execution of juſtice between man and man, without feare, and without partiality and alſo for any other thing, for freedom, and liberty, of Parliament and Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Againe it is ſaid, the golden cord of Government and Authority of Magiſtrates is broken, and laid in the duſt by them; for anſwer, it is ſo farre from being broken and laid in the duſt by them, that it is exalted, and made ſtrong by them, for they have been a meanes to ſet them in ſuch a poſture, they need not to feare; but be bold and couragious in acting for God, and his glorie, and be bold in the true execution of Juſtice, and you know Juſtice exalteth a Nation, ſo as there is a way made by them inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally to the exaltation of the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid they have made the Parliament contemptible, and torne them in ſunder in one day; to which it may be anſwered, they have ſet the Parliament in ſuch a condition, that if the Lord be pleaſed to give them hearts to lay hold of it, they may be more exalted and honoured then over Parliament was, for they are in ſuch freedome to act, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Parliament was before, for they have no negative voyce to trouble or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117684:19"/> hinder them, in going on in any good motion that God ſhall put into their mind, or any other can helpe them to underſtand by informing of them: and for their being torne in ſunder, I hope that is farre off, for I hope they are joyned more ſure together then ever, and there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares nothing contrary in their acting, but they are more then ever, and there is need they ſhould, having ſo many enemies to joyne againſt them, and they ſo few that ſtand to act cloſe for God, in ſeeking his glory, onely for being in ſuch a condition as they are, they have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſweetly to accord and agree together, and keep the <hi>unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace,</hi> they having obſtructions removed as they have been, and are.</p>
               <p>Again it is ſaid, they have gone againſt the Law of God, in what they have don in going againſt Magiſtrates, and are ſuch as God hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under paine of damnation, and ſo are like <hi>Caine,</hi> and <hi>Corah</hi> and his companie; and ſo are gathered together againſt the Lord, and ſo to be taken as wicked men, and rebells, and as if <hi>Jehu</hi> like, they murdered Kings under ſpecious pretences. For anſwer, They have done the Law of God, which ſaith, <hi>whoſoever ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> And <hi>thou ſhalt take n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> recompence for the life of a murtherer, for blood defileth the Land; and the Land cannot be purged of the blood that is ſhed; but by the blood of him that ſhed it:</hi> ſo as what they have done in bringing ſuch to tryall, hath been their dutie to God, the Covenant, and Kingdome, and therefore, are not ſuch as God will condemn, but approve of; and inſtead of going againſt Magiſtrates, they have, and do act, for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of them in their acting for God, and therefore they may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably expect a bleſſing from God, they being for God and their Covenant: and ſo are far unlike <hi>Caine,</hi> and <hi>Corah,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore do not deſerve the name of wicked men in their ſence, for they rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſervants of the Lord, to ſet up themſelves, and ſo have not theſe done yet. Nor are they to be accounted as Rebells, for they have been apprehending of Rebells, and have been ſo far from going againſt them that have acted for the glory of God, that they have act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their peace, and for the ſafety, preferment, and libertie, not only of ſuch of them as are in Parliament, but for thoſe that are al over the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore may be called more truly Saviours, then Rebells. And for Jeſuitiſh practiſes, for private perſons to murther Kings, It is very evill to apply this to them, for as hath been ſaid formerly, they were not private men, but publick, being ſet in publicke place by the higheſt Authoritie, and what they did was far from murther, for they did but bring him forth to Tryall, which the Covenant did bind them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117684:20"/> unto, and hee had his Tryall according to the power of the higheſt Court in the Kingdome, and therefore they are not to be called mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of Kings, nor in any degree to be held forth to be ſuch as have done any ſuch thing under ſpecious pretences.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, they do that which they would condemn in others, in poſſeſſing the Kings perſon, and carrying him from place to place, without and againſt the Parliaments conſent, and the like was in the removing the Parliaments guards, and continuing new modells de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to this and all other Parliaments, with other acts of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Anſwer, They have done that, which I hope they would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in others, and charity binds me ſo to thinke, for becauſe that they did was good; for, for ceazing the Kings perſon, was neceſſary for their own, the Parliament, and Kingdomes ſafety, that ſo hee might not be at his own, nor the Parliaments diſpoſe (at preſent) while there were ſo prevalent a party for him, which might have indangered all that which they had beene ſo long ſtriving for, and that had coſt ſo much blood and treaſure, and that it was ſo, appeareth in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Declaration, for they ſay there was a ſtrong party to hinder the good of the Kingdome. And for the removing of the King from place to place, that was to the ſame end.</p>
               <p>But whereas it is ſaid to be againſt the Parliaments conſent. Anſwer, it hath not appeared ſo, for they did never ſend to the Army to have him out of their hands; and beſides, they had him not ſo, but the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament might have free acceſſe to him at their pleaſure, and had, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they voted they would have no more; and yet afterward when their minds changed, they had accceſſe to him againe, and ſuch as might have hazzarded the good of the Kingdome, and Cauſe, and all; and beſides, they offered no wrong to him all the while they had him in their cuſtody, and for removing the Parliaments guards, what harme was in that, or cauſe of complaint? for the City was eaſed thereby of a burthen, and charge, for it was all one price, for the Souldiers muſt have been paid, if they had not done it, and for the Parliament they never complained of it: and for contriving new modells it hath been often anſwered, it was but propounded, but that, that which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded was deſtructive to this, and all other Parliaments I never yet underſtood, but it was for the better carrying on of this and all other Parliaments, and keeping them from corrupting, and eaſing them of the burthen of ſitting ſo long, before they have any reſpit, and ſetting the people of the Kingdome at liberty often in their choiſe, that ſo if they be miſtaken one time, they may endeavour to avoid it in the next, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117684:20"/> ſo one Parliament may amend if others have done amiſſe; and for other cauſes of the like nature, and you may ſee they were miſtaken in their thoughts of this Parliament, being ſet a time, but they ſit ſtill, and thoſe that propounded for their breaking up, are content, and I hope thankfull to God and them, that they are content to ſit and take pains for to ſettle the worke they have begun, and made ſo great a progreſſe in; and I hope I may ſay the like for many of the godly party in the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>And it is further ſaid, it was once thought of them a matter of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, of a high nature, to endeavour the deſtruction of fundamentall Lawes, and to diſſwade the calling of Parliaments, and the breaking up of Parliaments, and to countenance Arminians, and connive at Papiſts; and now, as if it were commendable in them to contrive the ſubverſion of the whole Laws and Government of the Kingdom, and to endeavour a totall univerſal Toleration, as they fear: Anſwer, it was indeed a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of offence of a high nature, for one man for the ſatisfaction of his owne will, to overthrow the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome; but that is not their caſe, for they would not have any alteration to bee made at the will of any one man; and for the fundamentall Lawes to be altered, that is not like to be, but is declared to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that was an offence of a high nature, to diſſwade from the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Parliaments; and therefore they ſeeing and feeling it to bee ſo great, they have deſired it may be prevented for time to come, a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being the next way of refuge and ſafety to the Nation under God; and the breaking of it up at the pleaſure of one man, was a great burthen, and high offence; and therefore they propoſe, that they might have their time ſet how long they ſhould ſit, that ſo they might not be broken up before, except they themſelves ſee fit ſo to do, for the good of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>And for what you ſpeake of Arminians and Papiſts, it was cauſe of griefe to every gracious heart, the one being groſſe Idolaters, and the other but little better; but in ſome ſenſe may be more dangerous and hurtfull: but your inference will not hold; as if it was commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to contrive the ſubverſion of the whole Lawes and government of the Kingdome, and to endeavour a totall and univerſall Toleration; for it doth not appeare that any, eſpecially thoſe whom you do write unto, doe account it a commendable thing to contrive the ſubverſion of the whole Lawes and government of the Kingdome, for they have not propounded that; and therefore how can any (without breach of charity) ſay they commend it: nor have they propounded for an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117684:21"/> Toleration, and therefore we dare not conclude they doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of either, and therefore they will never account it commendable, but that they will oppoſe it, and any that ſhall labour ſo to doe; and as they have been, ſo they will continue to be for the glory of God, and the good of the Kingdome, and for the good of the people of God, who we hope are deare unto them: And as for your feares you hold forth againſt perſons of ſuch eminent note, with no better grounds; we cannot but witneſſe againſt it as a ſin ſo to doe, being a breach of the 5. 6. and 9. Commandments.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, they are confident upon their former ſucceſſes, which is no good ground, eſpecially they being before in the wayes of God; but now they are not: Anſwer, if ever they might be confident of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, becauſe they were in the wayes of God, they might be now; for the way they are now in, is as much approved, as any way they ever walked in, ſince they tooke up Armes, for this did tend much to the conſummation of all they had laboured for, and the triall greater; and therefore for them to hold out, is a great ſigne that God is with them, and will be with them, and give them good ſucceſſes.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, there was no neceſſity of their ſo acting, but of their owne making, but they make a neceſſity to ſin: Anſwer, that there was a neceſſity is true, but that made, it doth not appeare; for the neceſſity lay in the power and greatneſſe of the parties they had to deal withall, which made the worke difficult, and ſo a neceſſity for them to act as they did: and although neceſſity doth not warrant to ſin, yet neceſſity may make that lawfull, which without neceſſity is unlawfull; as for <hi>David,</hi> and thoſe that were with him, to eat the ſhew-bread, was a ſin, had not neceſſity cauſed them to do it; but when they were in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they might eat it, and not ſin in ſo doing; and it might be ſhewne in many other things: and ſo it was your owne caſe in taking up Armes againſt the King, which had beene ſinfull, if neceſſity had not beene, and that doth continue ſtill: but they needed not to have plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſity, for they had the word of God, and the Covenant, which they had taken to beare them out, as hath beene formerly ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid, their neceſſity was doubtfull, and not cleare and certaine, becauſe it was ſeen by none but themſelves: Anſwer, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will not ſee, none can make them; but to them that will ſee, it was plaine enough; for any rationall man might ſee that there was nothing held forth by the King that could be a ground to thinke other, but that all ſhould be as bad as ever, if not worſe, if ever he came upon the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117684:21"/> Throne againe; nor any thing in thoſe Parliament men that were kept backe, that might be ground they would not act for the hurt of the Kingdome, they having ſo acted the laſt time they were there, by their voting, notwithſtanding the Army was in <hi>London,</hi> and the King was taken off from treating, and removed to another place; and therefore it could yeeld no hope, but that they that would ſo act in ſuch a time as that was, might goe further to the undoing of all, and therefore no further to be truſted in that kinde for the preſent.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, the Parliament did act freely for the Covenant, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they were forced by the Army: Anſwer, it is manifeſt they have acted for God, ſince thoſe members were kept backe, witneſſe their repealed Votes, and in their execution of Juſtice; but that they did ſo before, doth not appeare, but the contrary; witneſſe thoſe Votes they made, that are ſince Repealed, and the danger of them held forth by the Declaration of Parliament: And alſo it was clearly againſt the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant they acted for; is it not againſt the Covenant to ſhelter from Juſtice thoſe that had deſerved death by Treaſon? as Duke <hi>Hambleton,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> &amp;c. And is it not againſt the Covenant to keepe any Delinquents from triall, that they might receive condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? ſo that they were ſo farre from acting for the Covenant, as they acted againſt the Covenant.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, they are buſie-bodies in other mens matters: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it is true, they are buſie for the good of other men, even many thouſands, but they are buſie in the place they are called to, and fitted for by God, and in which they were ſet by the Parliament, who cauſed that to be their worke by appointment, as they were Souldiers; ſo as they are buſie in their owne worke for the Kingdomes good, and that was their duty, and they were faithfull in it, for the glory of God, the good of his people, and the Nation, and the cauſe they were to defend; and therefore to be commended for being ſo faithfull in their places; and they are to be prayed for to the Lord, that hee would keep them faithfull in their places, and keep them from turning, <hi>That they being faithfull to the death, the Lord may give them the Crowne of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray therefore conſider of all theſe particulars, and conſider, if it be not a ſad thing, ſo many of you, as 47. ſhould be found guilty of ſo many grievous ſinnes, as this is, to charge people with ſo many things, and can prove none; for all thoſe charges are ſins of a high nature, and ſome of them are ſinnes of a very high nature, and deſerve great and high puniſhments from God and man; and therefore doe render juſtly thoſe perſons deteſtable to God and man, that are guilty of ſuch
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117684:22"/> things as theſe: But if guiltles, then conſider what a condition ſuch men are in, as do thus charge perſons, although they be but of ordinary rank; if they canot prove what they charge them with, their ſin is very great; for we know, what the Lord hath ſaid againſt falſe witneſſes (thoſe that lay ſo many things to their charge as theſe have done, and not prove them, are falſe witneſſes in a high degree) and the Lord hath told us, looke what they intended to bring upon the party by ſuch witneſſe, the ſame ſhall be done to them; but how much more, when this is not done to one perſon, but to many, and that not to men of a meane ranke and place, but thoſe of a high ranke and place, and ſuch as have deſerved to be honoured for what they had done, and were doing, it being that the Law of God allows of, and the whole Kingdom hath cauſe to bleſſe God for, what ever may be held out to the contrary, by perſons diſ-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Kingdomes good, that may aime at their owne ends in ſo doing; and therefore God will finde out ſuch perſons, if men paſſe them by; and he will powre out contempt for contempt, and diſgrace for diſgrace, and reproach for reproach; for he is a juſt God, and hee knowes alſo the moſt ſecret workings of ſuch as worke againſt his people, for their owne ends, and their ſecret grudgings againſt them; and therefore we may ſay to ſuch, <hi>Be not deceived, for God is not, nor will not be mocked, for what a man, or men ſow, that they ſhall reap:</hi> But how much more is it to be admired, that ſuch as lay ſuch heavy burthens upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhould be more guilty of thoſe very things, if not greater, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and therefore it will not be amiſſe to examine whether they bee guilty, or not.</p>
               <p>May it not be ſaid, it was an unſeemly thing, if not too much ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy of ſpirit for you to call them private perſons, and account it an unſeemly thing for them to deſire a conſultation with you? for if they were private perſons, they were none of the meaneſt ſort, which if they had, you ſhould not have ſlighted them. Againe, have you not gone herein againſt a direct rule in the Word? or againſt many rules? have you not gone againſt the fifth and ſixth Commandement? and that of the Apoſtle, <hi>love thinketh no evill,</hi> and that, <hi>Judge nothing before the time.</hi> Nay, I wiſh you had not broken the third Commandement, by miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Word, if not miſ-interpreting the Word.</p>
               <p>Again, have you not don that which is out of your ſphere, in medling with matters of the Commonwealth in ſuch ſort as you have done, and with perſons in higheſt places in the Kingdome, and throwing filth upon them? And may not you be charged with former miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, if all that was written of ſome of your carriages in your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117684:22"/> in your morni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Lectures be true? which I may beleeve, becauſe I never heard it denied by you yet.</p>
               <p>May it not be truly ſaid, your late carriages have been againſt lawfull Authority, when you taxe Parliament and Army with things of ſo high an offence that have been done againſt the King? May it not be ſaid you oppoſe the Parliament, when you will not acknowledge them to be a Parliament? at leaſt not pray for them as a Parliament, and alſo oppoſe their proceedings, and that before, and to the whole world, ſo farre as in you lyes, and thereby take off the hearts of the people of the Kingdome from them, as much as in you lyes, and by juſtifying men to be eminent, and of worth, and integrity, which have been declared by the Parliament, to have acted directly againſt the good of the Kingdome? and this you have done ſince they ſo did: And it may bee ſaid, that which you have done is againſt lawfull Authority, and Magiſtrates that God hath ſet over us, and contrary to the duty you owe unto them by the law of God and man; nay which is yet more againſt your Oathes and Covenants, which you ſo plead for; for if that which they did, was in performance of the Covenant, as hath been ſaid formerly, then what you have done muſt needs be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
               <p>And may it not be ſaid you have gone againſt all thoſe Scriptures you have alledged againſt them in that kind? for if the Word ſpeak againſt them for doing any thing, if you do the ſame, it will take hold of you as well as of them. And have not you done ſomething without colour of authority of the Word of God, if it be taken in a right ſence, and not abuſed? And have not you gone againſt your truſt and many Ingagements, in oppoſing what you have done, tending to overthrow that for which ſo much blood and treaſure have been ſhed for, which was the purity of the Ordinances, and in bringing us into a worſe condition then ever wee were in before the Warres began; and you were preſerved in your places by them, that ſo you might preſerve them in purity, and do you not go againſt it, and ſhew your diſcontent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are removed, which did hinder it? And do you not uſurpe authority over the Parliament and Army, ſo far as you can, with your clamours and threatnings? if we may judge your hearts by your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, you make high oppoſition.</p>
               <p>And may it not truly be ſaid, you meddle with things not belonging to you? did it belong to you to write in controle of the Proceedings of the Parliament and Army as you have done, and ſo to take off the hearts of the people from both? And is not your doings irregular,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117684:23"/> and tending to the overthrow of Religion, while you ſeek to preſerve them that would do it. And O that it might not be truly ſaid! you are fallen from your former Judgements, and Principles, of <hi>Curſe you Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz, becauſe they came not out to helpe the Lord againſt the Mighty,</hi> for now you do little better to thoſe that have, and doe helpe. And are not you in ſuch a condition that the people of God that underſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, dare not, nor may not bid you God ſpeed, nor wiſh you well in the name of the Lord in this action? and ſuch like. And do not theſe your deſires tend to open a doore to Popery and Prelacy, while as you plead for them that will bring in both? And may it not be truly ſaid, that Religion is made to ſtinke by your meanes? when you that are Teachers of others in it, and profeſſe your ſelves ſo to be, doe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly diſgrace thoſe that ſeeke to maintaine it in the moſt pure manner, and plead for thoſe that would throw it downe; and that you ſhould be turned from what you were in the beginning of the Parliament: and if it doe not make Religion ſtinke, yet there is cauſe the faces of Gods people ſhould be covered with ſhame for your miſcarriages in this thing, and our hearts filled with ſorrow and griefe; and the Government of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the courage and faithfulneſſe of the Army, by you is ſought to be laid in the duſt, and ſo have made them contemptible.</p>
               <p>And let it be conſidered, if your cauſe may not be compared to <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> yea, whither it will not ſuite with <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, for they rebelled againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in their acting for God; and have not you done the like againſt the godly Party in Parliament, and Kingdome, which may appeare by what hath been formerly ſaid, and in that ſence may you not be called Rebels? And may it not be more truly ſaid of you, in your acting in this paper, that you act the parts of <hi>Jeſabels,</hi> while you ſeeke, under pretence of the Covenant, to caſt filth upon the Parliament and Army, ſtirring up the people to ſlight, if not to contemne and rebell againſt them, and ſo be a meanes to hinder all that good they have laboured and endeavoured to procure, if not ſtirre up to another warre.</p>
               <p>And may it not be further ſaid, you doe that which you condemne in others, when you condemne others for breaking the Covenant, and yet you doe it your ſelves? and condemne others for not obeying the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and you doe not obey it your ſelves; nay contemne it, or ſlight it at the beſt, and condemne others for reſiſting the powers, and you doe it your ſelves, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And may it not be truly ſaid of you, that the time was, you did think they did exceeding evill that did not goe out to warre, againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117684:23"/> of the Kingdome, and bring them to triall, if not deſtroy them, and now you are againſt them that ſo doe? And aske Conſcience, if you have not ſlighted providence when it hath ſo wonderfully appeared, to the juſt offence of many a godly heart, and therefore much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that, that hath declared himſelfe ſo wonderfully for us; witneſſe your not taking notice of them, and that when you have been injoyned to doe it by the higheſt Authority in the Kingdome; and alſo ſlighted the ſucceſſes: formerly you have kept dayes of Thankſgiving, for provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and ſucceſſes, but now you ſlight both, although they be as great, if not greater then ever before.</p>
               <p>And whereas you tax them for being led by the impulſe of ſpirit, it may be truly ſaid, in this you were not led by the Spirit of God, for that is pure and peaceable; but it is to be feared you are led by the contrary ſpirit in this, or by your owne ſpirit at the beſt; and if any evill ſhould have befalne you by this your acting, it might truly have been ſaid, it had been contracted by your owne miſcarriages; and may it not be truly ſaid of you that you were beautifull, when you acted for God, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Warres, but now you are cut of his waies, and therefore you may feare he, and his, will forſake you; or at leaſt he will ſuffer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to be brought upon you. And may we not admire to heare you ſay, they were acting freely for that which was Covenanted for, untill the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came and forced them? was it Covenanted, that all ſhould be brought againe into the old Channell, or into a worſe condition then they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Warres began, as hath been formerly ſpoken to? and therefore conſider who may looke for the flying Roll, and who are to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted buſie-bodies in other mens matters; and therefore the Lord give every of you a heart to conſider, that the mouth of the Cannon may not be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt your ſelves, I meane thoſe charges you have laid upon them: and which is more, thoſe Scriptures which ſhould be as Cannons indeed, which we ſhould not ſtand againſt, but fall before them when they come againſt us, eſpecially thoſe, or the moſt of them which you have brought againſt them, as I have hinted before, for if theſe things be thus, have not all the people of God cauſe, (eſpecially the Miniſters that have not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended as you have done) to crie aloud, and ſhew you your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and your ſinne; and conſider if they doe hold their peace, whether they doe not make themſelves guilty of your ſins, and if we muſt not have fellowſhip with the unfruitfull workes of darkneſſe?</p>
               <p>I beſeech you conſider what hath been ſaid, and ſee if you have not bin ſuch in this act, and if we are bidden to abſtaine from all appearance of evill, how much more from reall evill? and if you conſider what hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117684:24"/> been ſaid, you will ſee yours reall as well in this; and therefore it muſt follow, that the people of God muſt abſtaine from you, and have no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with you, while you act in this manner; and if we muſt not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with them that are ſubject to change, then by what hath been ſaid we muſt not meddle with you, for have not you changed, when you crie out againſt what you formerly cryed out for? and crie downe that which formerly you have cryed up? and if we muſt withdraw from every Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that walkes diſorderly, then, we beſeech you, ſee, if you be not the men by what hath been ſaid, and by what your ſelves have ſaid, and what your ſelves can ſay? who know more of the ſecrets of your owne hearts then any other man, or men: but the fruits we may judge by your owne inſtance, I take it, and that may moſt prevaile with you, if it be as your ſelves ſay, it is diſorderly not to be ſubject to Principalities, and obey Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, if you be not the men, conſider; beſides, all your expreſſions in prayer thoſe daies of Humiliation, and thoſe daies of Thankſgiving that have been commanded of late, may ſufficiently declare to all that have been neare you. Nay, hath it not further appeared, when you have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to caſt an odium upon them, not only in our owne Land, but in all others, ſo far as in you lyes; by your cauſing it to be put in print; and you have further ſhewed it, by doing the like upon their proceedings, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Armie, which they have ſet up, and as is in print, by giving them unſeemly termes, and reproachfull, all which your ſelves cannot endure; and doe you thinke your ſelves better then they? and is not this the way to bring them into contempt, and is it not againſt that text you bring in the <hi>Romans</hi> 13.1, 2. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God;</hi> and is not the Parliament a power? and is not the Armie a power? nay, what is there ſaid further, <hi>He that reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God;</hi> nay, he that ſo doth, ſhall receive dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. What will you ſay, and how will you anſwer it before the Lord at the laſt day? and how can you anſwer Conſcience at preſent, when it gripes you with it? what can I ſay why I ſhould not receive dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if I continue ſtill in this condition, eſpecially when you think you made uſe of it to make others troubleſome? and may not that text be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to you, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.14, 15.18, 19. He that hath broken the Covenant ſhall he proſper? he ſhall not proſper: the Lord ſhew you in mercy, how much, and how often you have broken the Covenant, and doe ſtill, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially you crying ſo as you doe againſt thoſe that ſo doe; and doe you not heare the voice within, Shall I proſper? I ſhall not, I cannot, it is the Lord that hath ſpoken it, and I my ſelfe have applied it to others; and ſay further, ſurely the Kingdome hath no cauſe to ſay, We bleſſe you in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117684:24"/> the name of the Lord, or the bleſſing of the Lord be upon you; nor to bid you good ſpeed in this you have done, wherein you have done ſo manie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill deeds, but to follow your counſell that you give others againſt the Armie, that ſo we may not be partakers with you in thoſe evill deeds; and that in <hi>Jude</hi> doth come fully upon you, for you have ſpoken evill of dignities, and have deſpiſed their dominion, and therefore all that text be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to you; and have you not run after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and I wiſh, it be not for a reward, and therefore perſiſting, may you not feare you ſhall periſh in the gaine-ſaying of <hi>Corah;</hi> and alſo have not you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and ſo may apply that text to your ſelves, for have not you cried out, the Parliament and Armie have taken too much upon them? and is not this act of yours, in gathering together ſo many of you, is it not againſt the Lord, while you gather together againſt them that are acting for the Lord? and may not that text in the ſame ſence you apply it to others, be applied to your ſelves, while you goe on in the ſame way? and there were a conſiderable companie of them eminent men, and famous in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and would not you be thought to be ſo? and are not there manie of you in this? and you have in ſome ſence exceeded them, for they did but ſpeake againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> but you have not only ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but written, and cauſed it to be printed, that ſo it might be ſent all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the world; and therefore conſider how fitly that text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. Are not you the men that have done ſuch things? that have condemned that in others that you doe your ſelves; and therefore we cannot but thinke that you apprehend it to be a vertue, and doe not you delight in them that doe as you have done? and if ſo, then aske your Conſciences, if you be not the men that have done things worthy of death? and alſo that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. And thinkeſt thou oh man that judgeſt, and doeſt the ſame things, that thou ſhalt eſcape the Judgement of God? but you have done that, you have judged others; for as contemning powers, and Magiſtrates, and verſ. 2.6. &amp; 11. we are ſure the Judgement of God is according to truth to them that doe ſuch things, who will render to everie one according to his workes: and there is no reſpect of perſons with God; except it be you that have more meanes by your parts, gifts, and places, God will looke for more from your hands, as is ſaid of <hi>Corazin,</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida</hi> in another kinde; and may not that text in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> be applied to you? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſentence againſt an evill worke is not executed; therefore the hearts of the children of men are ſet in them to doe evil. You have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken largely before, and no body oppoſed you, and now you have not only ſpoken, but written, and ſo the world may take notice of it, and is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this a great evill? And further, I beſeech you to conſider, if you have not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117684:25"/> miſ-applyed thoſe Texts 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 14.4. and, 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 26.8, 9. and <hi>Job</hi> 13.7. For wherein have they done wickedly for God, or have not you done ſo? and that flying Rowle you ſpeak of, may it not be more truly applyed to you, then to them? as hath been formerly ſaid, who have been breakers of that Solemne Oath and Covenant.</p>
               <p>And although you have not done violence to the Parliament; and Armie, in their perſons; yet have you not offered violence to their names? witneſſe what is in Print in Mr. <hi>Prices</hi> book, in anſwer to your Letter. And have not you accuſed them falſlie, that have laid ſo many falſe things to their charge, as is formerlie ſhewed? And it were to bee deſired, you would be as wel content with your wages as they have bin, &amp; conſider if they have not gon beyond you, in being ſo content as they have been, for they have not only been content with their wages, but they have been content to be without their wages, which if it had been your caſe, it is to be feared, the Citie and Countrie ſhould have heard of it by you, as injuſtice; and juſtlie you might have don ſo, but where, or when have you ſpoken for this on their behalf, although it hath bin the cauſe of many evills, as diſcontents, diſcouragement in the Souldier, and oppreſſion of manie by free Quarter, and ſo to raiſe up the ſpirits of the Countrie to hate them, and deſpiſe them, whom they have ſo much cauſe to eſteem, and honour, for what they have ſo faithfully done, in defending the Countrie, and offending their enemies; and if the labourer be worthie of his hire for a daies worke, when he may worke without danger; is not he much more, that goes in danger of his life ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rie daie, and houre, in defence of his Countrie, and the Cauſe of God eſpeciallie? and yet it ſeemes, that you have not taken ſo much notice of it as you ſhould, becauſe you have ſpoken no more in their behalfe, and may you not fear, if you perſiſt in your way ſtill, that which is ſaid in <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.23. <hi>You have ſinned, &amp; your ſin will find you out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, you have beene threatned if you perſiſt in ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up ſedition among the people, the Lord helpe you to conſider if it be not ſo. But whereas you ſay, your bewayling their ſins before God is accounted ſo; it may be feared, you ſpeak againſt your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in ſaying ſo; if you ſpeake not againſt conſcience, you ſpeake againſt charity: I intreat you, aske conſcience, if you think, that hee that, you ſay, threatned you, did thinke, that bewayling of ſinne, before God, bee ſedition? But it may be in that time when you ſay you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle your ſinnes before the Lord, and among your bewaylings, you might have ſome or many ſeditious expreſſions, or expreſſions tending to Sedition: And I beſeech you, aske conſcience if it hath not been ſo,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117684:25"/> for you know what is in Print, and that was that you were adviſed to take heed of, and, it may be, you account that threatning of you, which if you did, it was evill done of you, for it was a friendly part ſo to doe; and if you ſhould do ſo, you did adde ſin to ſin.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſpeak, you were threatned, that ſome might doe you miſchiefe, if they had, I fear you would have had but a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in it: And as for ſtirring up diſcontents in the people, and ſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion another War; what miſchiefe ſoever ſhould befall any thereby, might lie heavy upon you.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, you have delivered your owne ſouls, you may rather conſider that Text, <hi>Who required theſe things at your hands? for if thy brother offend, tell him between him &amp; thee:</hi> have you done ſo? or if you ſay you dare not, you ſhould have bewayled it before the Lord: But when did you ever read that you ſhould publiſh it unto the world by, writing and Printing of it before it was publickly made known by others: nay, you refuſed to go, when you were ſent for, to them, and might have had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to tell them ſo; and inſtead of delivering your own ſouls, you have further ſtained them; and inſtead of ſuffering, as Chriſtians, for well-doing, you may feare you ſhall ſuffer for your evill-doing; and inſtead of thoſe ſufferings, being acceptable before God, there is cauſe to feare, it is highly diſpleaſing to God, and greatly to his diſhonour: And although the death of his Saints bee precious in his ſight, yet it could not be for your comfort to dye in ſuch a condition, or for ſuch an act as this is, in ſetting forth ſuch a Book.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>When he makes inquiſition for bloud, he forgets not the humble:</hi> The Lord helpe you to ſee how little humility you have ſhewed in this booke, from the beginning, to the end of it: I know not what you can make appeare to your ſelves; but I feare, an humble judicious Reader, can finde very little in it, but much of the contrary; for is it not through pride man makes contention? and what this book could doe leſſe, let the judicious and conſcientious Reader judge, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out at ſuch a time as it did; Is it not through pride, that men that be ſent for in a loving and honourable way to be conſulted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; in weighty matters, and refuſe to goe upon ſuch termes as is ſet downe? Is it not pride to ſet up our ſelves above others, eſpecially ſuch as are in high degree? Is it not pride to call others but private men in reſpect of our ſelves, that are above us in publicke place ſet by the Lord? Is it not pride for us to meddle in things too high for us, which God hath not imployed us in? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And whereas, you ſay, you were told, if you put your ſelves upon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117684:26"/> ſuffering, you might have ſuffering enough: Is it not true, for who can either have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omfort in ſufferings, or expect to get out of them, that pull them needleſly upon themſelves? eſpecially by venturing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unlawfull courſes as this of yours is: and therefore how can you ſay, The God whom you ſerve, will deliver you, when in this you doe not ſerve the God of heaven, who is the God, I hope, you meane: And therefore, I beſeech you, conſider if you doe not abuſe his name, in ſo ſaying, as if he would patronize a thing that is ſo evil as this is; it is true, in the diſcharge of your duty, that he calls you unto, you may commit your ſoules into his hands as to a faithfull Creator: but this is not a worke that he ſet you about, or will owne; and therefore you cannot ſo commit your ſoules to him while you go on in ſuch ſinfull waies.</p>
               <p>All theſe things conſidered, how will it appeare that what you have done, is out of zeale to Gods glory, for he is, and will be much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by this writing: neither can you ſay, you have diſcharged your duty, for it is not your duty to diſhonour God, as you have done by this: And how can any thinke that it is with an earneſt deſire after the comfort and ſalvation of their ſoules, when you ſpeake with that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe as you have done, and laid ſo many falſe things to their charge? and is not this to ſpeake wickedly for God?</p>
               <p>It is true, you have ſpoken freely, but I wiſh it might not be ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully; but if it be not ſo, I deſire any judicious, conſcientious, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Reader, to judge. It may be you have declared your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but I would hope the contrary; for if this be your judgements, it ſhewes, they be very corrupt, whereas you have ſpoken ſo much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, and many untruths againſt them both for their former and latter proceedings; for ſhould you be ſatisfied in your deſires? all would have been in a worſer condition then they were before the blood and treaſure was ſpent, for not onlie an enemie ſhould have been let looſe upon us, but an enemie enraged; and therefore if that ſhould have refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in your ſence, all the Church of Chriſt would have had great cauſe of mourning and ſadneſſe for what they had yeelded unto, and we might have taken it as a juſt recompence for our ſin; but their not taking your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, we have cauſe to bleſſe the Lord for, and that he hath made them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall to ſet forth his glorie, and alſo a mercie, and ſalvation, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement to his people; and ſo you found falſe Prophets as well as you have bin falſ accuſers, in what you ſay that their preſent actings do certainly tend to miſerie and confuſion; but oh that it might not truly be ſaid, that your preſent actings, if for the ſin of the Kingdome you ſhould prevaile, they will bring unavoidable miſerie and confuſion: Oh therefore that the Lord would pleaſe to ſet things ſadly upon your hearts, and bring you to a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117684:26"/> ſerious and ſad conſideration of what you have done; you have had divers anſwers formerly, and therein the Lord hath appeared divers waies unto you, in his offers of conviction, which ſeeme ſome tokens of his favour unto you, if he give you a heart to ſearch, and ſee what his will is towards you in it: Conſider therefore, I beſeech you, what your ſelves are by your owne account, in reſpect of your places and ſtanding, and doe not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw ſuch honourable ſtandings, places, and titles, &amp;c. by diſhonourable waies: I beſeech you conſider, will you take the name of Miniſters of the Goſpel, Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, and Paſtors of Churches, all honourable titles, but how unlike you have acted, others have told you, and the Lord grant you may conſider it: but for ſuch as have ſuch titles, or challenge themſelves, conſider, for you to doe, and ſpeake, and write ſuch things, which make the enemies of God to take content in, if not rejoice in, and to gratifie Malignants, and to grieve the people of God, and ſad their hearts, if not all of them, yet a great manie of them that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his waies; and that it ſhould be ſaid of you, as if you ſhould be Incendiaries, to ſtir up the evill affected to another warre, and ſo to daunt the hearts of manie of the people of God, ſo as their hearts ſhould ſinke, ſo as they ſhould queſtion their way; nay, lead ſome of them to be forward in oppoſing the way of truth and peace.</p>
               <p>Againe, conſider not only you give yourſelves theſe titles, but that you ſay you are within the Province of <hi>London,</hi> (although it ſeeme by the writing of ſome you are not all of you ſo) ſo thoſe that are within the Province of London, where you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are one another, and ſo may be helps one to another; what, in the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> the chiefe Citie in the Kingdome, that hath been famous for the Goſpell, for ſo manie to joyn together in ſuch a calumniating Letter as this was, againſt ſuch perſons as this is againſt; is it not an evil example to the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? for you may pleaſe to conſider, the generality of the people are led more by example then by precept, and more by the precepts of men then of God, eſpecially of them that are in ſuch places as you are in; for you are, or at leaſt ſhould be the lights of the world, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>But if the light that is in you be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe?</hi> Oh what a ſad thing it is to heare the people ſay, the Miniſters are moſt diſcontent with what is done, and for you to ſtir up diſcontents in the people, and make them fit to contrive new deſignes to bring more miſerie, if not ruine to this poore Kingdom; and how ſad a thing is it to heare people ſay (eſpecially the people of God) if ruine and miſerie come upon the Kingdome, We may thanke our Miniſters next our ſins? Againe, conſider the time when you did this, when the greateſt buſineſſe was in hand that ever was in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Juſtice was in a good readineſſe to be executed, and upon the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117684:27"/> point of execution, and in ſuch a ſort as you could not but heare the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the Kingdom was diſcontented with, and crying out againſt, and ſo the worke was verie difficult in it ſelfe; but then for you to come in to gratifie thoſe perſons, aske your Conſcience what that muſt worke that was for his preſervation, and ſetting him up in his throne againe? Againe, aske your Conſciences what you thinke of manie of them that were againſt what was done? were not ſuch as would have hindred that work which you proſecuted, for the moſt part of them, Papiſts, Cavaliers, and Malignants, and prophane people? and doe you not feare to goe with thoſe, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them? and the moſt part of thoſe that were for it, if you aske Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience it will tell you, they were ſuch as have ſome feare of God before their eyes, and are ſuch as goe on conſcientiouſly in performance of the Covenant, and is it that Chriſt allowes? to have thoſe oppoſed, and ſpoken againſt, and diſheartened, for doing that, the Law of God, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant call them to doe? nay, to have ſuch perſons ſtirred up, and inveterate again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them that doe it?</p>
               <p>I beſeech you conſider, and feare, if herein you doe not fight againſt God; and would it not make a gracious heart mourne, to ſee ſo many that call themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel, ſervants and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, to go ſo directly againſt his Rules, which he hath ſet down in his holy word for us to walk by; the Lord in mercy help you to conſider it, and lay it to heart; what a ſad thing is it, that you th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t preach Chriſt, as you ſay, and are his Ambaſſadors, ſhould be ſo unlike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im in life, and converſation; Chriſt bids us, <hi>Learn of him, he is humble and meek, and when he was reviled, he reviled not againe:</hi> but in this ye have done, here appears pride and paſſion; and inſtead of not reviling, when you are reviled, you revile thoſe that are doing you good, ſo as you reward evill for good: nay, you revile thoſe that have, and were venturing their lives, to ſave the lives of you and yours: nay, all the godly part of the Kingdome: nay, you revile them for doing it: Oh againe, I beſeech you, examine your own conſciences, how you thinke to anſwer it before the Lord Chriſt, at the great day, when you muſt appeare before Him, Angels, Men and Devils; and once at the laſt, if it may be, ſmite upon your owne hearts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Lord to helpe you to be willing to take, and bear the ſhame of it here, by a free and full confeſſion, that ſo you may avoid everlaſting ſhame for ever, and ever. Oh, what ſhall I further ſay, <hi>Tell it not in Gath, nor publiſh it in Askelon;</hi> yea, but that it is too late; you have done it your ſelves, and now we cannot helpe it, nor well free our hands of it, but by witneſſing againſt it: for my part, I could rather have taken the part of <hi>Shem</hi> to <hi>Jephtah,</hi> to have gone far to have covered it; but that you have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117684:27"/> not onely been naked, but you have ſpread your nakedneſſe, and laid it open to the world, and ſo it is broder then can be covered, and ſo I am ſtopped there.</p>
               <p>And I could have been willing to obſerve the Rule of Chriſt, <hi>If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offend, tell him between thee and him;</hi> but you have put it paſt that, &amp; have put me upon the Rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that ſinneth openly, rebuke him openly;</hi> but I have forborne it as much as I could, to be faithfull in what I have undertaken: my aime is, if the will of God be, that he would by ſome meanes, ſhew you your ſinne; and bring you to repentance, that ſo as you have diſhonoured God by your ſinne, you might honour him by your acknowledgement of your ſin, that the Rule of God, and the people of God, may have ſome ſatisfaction, that as you have grieved them by your ſin you may rejoyce them in your repentance &amp; humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; for godlineſſe appears in power, when it workes the heart to bear ſhame and take ſhame openly for their ſin; for it is a perſons weakneſſe to fall into ſin, but it is his ſtrength to riſe againe by repentance, and acknowledging of it freely, which the Lord in mercy helpe you to doe.</p>
               <p>One argument more before I leave, give me leave to preſent unto you, which is the worke you are going about, which is the ſetting up of the Presbyterian Government: for may not wiſe men reaſon thus; Are theſe men fit to governe the Church of Chriſt, by having all the power put into their hands, when ſo many of them in one Province, and that the chiefeſt in the Kingdome, that are ſo neare together, which may take counſell one of, and with another; and if they miſcarry ſo ſhamefully, what ſhall we looke for in the other parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if they dare thus to confront the powers of the Kingdome, in the condition they are now in? what will they doe, if they get the power in their hand? and how will they lord it over the poore people, that muſt be under them? and they may ſuſpect you, by your eager deſire you have to have the power all in your owne hand; for they may well know, that a conſcientious humble heart, will feare to take the burthen of teaching, much more of ruling a Congregation, but will be farre from deſiring to take it upon him alone, or with one or two to helpe, but will be glad of the helpe of all in the Congregation to be joyned in power with him; and alſo to watch over him alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fearfull he ſhould miſcarry, and being willing to be helped, if hee ſo doe, as we may inſtance in this preſent act of yours; if any of theſe Miniſters had but a company of godly people in their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that would have called them to an account, and had power ſo to doe, they would have feared to have done ſuch an act as this was; or if
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117684:28"/> they had, they ſhould have been made to give publicke ſatisfaction: And may it not be feared, they know it well enough, and therefore they thinke to make it ſure, they will have the power in their owne hand, that ſo they may combine together, if occaſion ſerve, as they did now, and have none to call them to account: And this conſidered, I ſee not, but the Lord may have a hand in it, to keep you from that power you ſeeke, and give his people hearts to imbrace ſuch a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church, as Chriſt does approve of, that ſo he may ride in Triumph in Church and Commonwealth.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117684:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
